<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Amanda Winegardner on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>/tags/amanda-winegardner/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Amanda Winegardner on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 16:31:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/amanda-winegardner/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The battle of zooplankton</title>
      <link>/post/the-battle-of-zooplankton/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 16:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-battle-of-zooplankton/</guid>
      <description>Kaleigh Eichel, a student in Knowledge Integration, did research in Churchill for two summers. In addition to her research, she also created a web site translating some of the research in Churchill to the general public. One of the episodes features the projects done by Amanda and Brittany:
http://www.avioyak.ca/episode3.html&amp;nbsp;

Enjoy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amanda&#39;s adventures in the North continue.</title>
      <link>/post/amandas-adventures-in-the-north-continue./</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2011 09:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/amandas-adventures-in-the-north-continue./</guid>
      <description>The story telling is just happening in a different spot:&amp;nbsp;http://churchillscience.blogspot.com/2011/11/and-results-are-in-at-least-this-round.html. But it is still the heady combination of field research, guns, and statistics&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Showcase of Let&#39;s Talk Microbes</title>
      <link>/post/showcase-of-lets-talk-microbes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2011 09:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/showcase-of-lets-talk-microbes/</guid>
      <description>Last November, Marina and Amanda went to Kobe&amp;rsquo;s school to givea hands-on demonstration of microbes. The science teacher who invited them then nominated their activity to the Let&amp;rsquo;s Talk Science CIHR-Synapse award, a national competition. And they were selected as one of the 4 best showcase activities! And in the accompanying picture, you can see Amanda, Marina in the background, and my son Kobe with the spiderman sweater. How cool is all that?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy day - sad day, part 1</title>
      <link>/post/happy-day-sad-day-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2011 09:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/happy-day-sad-day-part-1/</guid>
      <description>All good things come to an end. And now it is Amanda&#39;s time to leave. She successfully defended her thesis &#34;Zooplankton metacommunity responses to environmental change in the sub-arctic&#34;. At this point, there are 3 manifestations of her work:Amanda&#39;s electronic thesis link: the UoG library now provides an electronic reference for all theses, which will increase the exposure and accessibility of the research.Her presentation, that is the perfect example of how we should present results to a larger audience</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Translating research</title>
      <link>/post/translating-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 13:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/translating-research/</guid>
      <description>Amanda is currently trying to publish the first chapter of her thesis (whohoo), and this can do funny things to your brain. See the post on her personal blog on how research findings are translated through the different media outlets, or the scientific version of telephone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s talk ... microbes</title>
      <link>/post/lets-talk-...-microbes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2010 12:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/lets-talk-...-microbes/</guid>
      <description>Amanda and Marina created a module to introduce Grade 1 kids to microbes for the programLet&amp;rsquo;s talk science. They picked a very challenging subject to introduce something we cannot see to 6 year-olds. However, they pulled it off very successfully using pictures, glow-in-the-dark powder and black lights, and a couple of microscope. I joined them for the final presentation (in my son&amp;rsquo;s class), and these are the pictures I took.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confessions of a grad student</title>
      <link>/post/confessions-of-a-grad-student/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2010 11:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/confessions-of-a-grad-student/</guid>
      <description>Are you intrigued by these snippets?I like statsI dislike learning R&amp;nbsp;results may be meaninglessTedious? Yes. Accurate? Yes&amp;nbsp;Then go over to&amp;nbsp;Amanda&#39;s latest blog post.&amp;nbsp; </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientists measure...</title>
      <link>/post/scientists-measure.../</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2010 15:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/scientists-measure.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; all kinds of things. See Amanda&amp;rsquo;s latest post from Churchill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Field work is winding down in Churchill</title>
      <link>/post/field-work-is-winding-down-in-churchill/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2010 15:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/field-work-is-winding-down-in-churchill/</guid>
      <description>Mid august, and it is starting to feel like summer is indeed slowly winding down.
Amanda is also feeling signs ofFall in Churchill, and Brittany has just put an update about her first field season up there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More science outreach in Churchill</title>
      <link>/post/more-science-outreach-in-churchill/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 13:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/more-science-outreach-in-churchill/</guid>
      <description>see here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A preview</title>
      <link>/post/a-preview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2010 12:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/a-preview/</guid>
      <description>A preview of things to come in the subarctic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amanda&#39;s hatching experiment</title>
      <link>/post/amandas-hatching-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2010 09:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/amandas-hatching-experiment/</guid>
      <description>Ecology in action, life, in Churchill, with pictures, and explanations, using the magic of tupperware. Who said science is boring and expensive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sub-arctic outreach</title>
      <link>/post/sub-arctic-outreach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jun 2010 13:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sub-arctic-outreach/</guid>
      <description>Is it possible that grade 3 kids are more interested in zooplankton than 3year university students? Click here to find out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amanda&#39;s first blog post of the season</title>
      <link>/post/amandas-first-blog-post-of-the-season/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2010 13:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/amandas-first-blog-post-of-the-season/</guid>
      <description>about trains, plains, and canoes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer 2010 fieldwork has begun!</title>
      <link>/post/summer-2010-fieldwork-has-begun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2010 23:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/summer-2010-fieldwork-has-begun/</guid>
      <description>The Cottenie lab will be active in Churchill, Manitoba again this year. I arrived in Churchill about a week ago and Brittany will be joining me in a few short weeks. Check out our progress as Planktoneers!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The world of conferences</title>
      <link>/post/the-world-of-conferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2010 16:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-world-of-conferences/</guid>
      <description>I also had the opportunity to attend a conference this week, the 5th annual meeting of the Canadian Society for Ecology and Evolution, held at the Universite Laval. It was a well organized conference with a lot of energy and some very interesting talks and posters. Quebec City served as a wonderful setting for the conference and I was impressed by how the conference was truly bilingual. I was also impressed by vieux Quebec and the beauty of the St.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out with rote learning</title>
      <link>/post/out-with-rote-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2010 10:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/out-with-rote-learning/</guid>
      <description>Tom Nudds and I co-taught community ecology for the first time together last semester (and Amanda was one of our wonderful TAs). Despite our differences ;-), we share a very similar teaching philosophy. And as a result of some crazy ideas, we decided to completely remodel community ecology. Tom&amp;rsquo;s rallying cry:
Out with rote learningTo implement this, we cut out all &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; aspects of grading in our course, and instead we implemented 3 research projects in a problem-based learning framework.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some pre fieldwork fieldwork</title>
      <link>/post/some-pre-fieldwork-fieldwork/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 22:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/some-pre-fieldwork-fieldwork/</guid>
      <description>Today Brittany and I took a walk over to the Arboretum to sample some of the temporary and man-made ponds, as part of an ongoing metacommunity study. With the warm spring we&amp;rsquo;ve been having, the zooplankton are in full swing, rivalling the communities we found in Churchill last year in August!Here Brittany is marvelling at the zooplankton and many aquatic insects:

Notice the tea-coloured water, it is stained by tannins leaching from the fallen leaves and detritus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are you? Zooplankton? Hahahahahahahaha.</title>
      <link>/post/what-are-you-zooplankton-hahahahahahahaha./</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2010 17:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/what-are-you-zooplankton-hahahahahahahaha./</guid>
      <description>After a whole month of preparations, it finally happened: the procession of species. It started a little bit late for us, since I had a race in the morning. But thanks to cell phones, we could join the parade half way through. Kobe was really excited and waiting for the first sign of the parade and the rest of the lab.
Here are some random pictures of the different species and musicians bringing life music.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The latest Birdfish</title>
      <link>/post/the-latest-birdfish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2010 18:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-latest-birdfish/</guid>
      <description>The Churchill Northern Studies Centre has hosted researchers from the Cottenie lab for the past couple years. This year we were invited to contribute a short write-up on our summer 2009 field season. You can read the article here:
http://www.churchillscience.ca/documents/Newsletter_Winter_2010.pdf
Also, be sure to check out the CNSC&amp;rsquo;s website for a preview of their new facility! The staff and volunteers at the CNSC are very supportive and a terrific resource for anyone doing science in the north.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More costumes</title>
      <link>/post/more-costumes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2010 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/more-costumes/</guid>
      <description>How many do you need to make a costume? Apparently more than 5. However, based on this last evening, we now have a full design, including the know-how on how to make it. So the next time we meet, we should have 6 full Daphnia costumes for the parade.&amp;nbsp;4 degrees to work with papier mache, your quality education at work
To illustrate that this is part of the rostrum, all you dirty minds&amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This is why we do this ...</title>
      <link>/post/this-is-why-we-do-this-.../</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2010 13:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/this-is-why-we-do-this-.../</guid>
      <description>research or science or playing or fun or exploration or whatever you want to call it.

Some background: Amanda, Ingrid, and Erin performed a very novel experiment in Churchill last summer (see their blog for more fun stuff). Amanda processed all the samples and is in the process of analyzing the data. Because of the design, it gets complicated very quickly, and so Amanda is honing her R-skills to visualize the results before we go p-value hunting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let the costumes begin!</title>
      <link>/post/let-the-costumes-begin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Mar 2010 10:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/let-the-costumes-begin/</guid>
      <description>Well, as Karl has mentioned our lab will be participating as a horde of zooplankton in the KW Procession of Species Parade. The parade is as much about encouragaing local expressions of art as it is about showcasing biodiversity. With that in mind we set out yesterday to stretch our creativity and construct a prototype of our first costume. We decided that Daphnia would be our main inspiration and started on a carapace and post abdomen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Awards galore</title>
      <link>/post/awards-galore/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2010 11:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/awards-galore/</guid>
      <description>Amanda and Ingrid both received an NSERC award: Amanda to finish her MSc, and Ingrid to start her PhD. Now she will have to make a decision ;-) Running a lab with such talented people is easy, I hardly have to do anything myself.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>