<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>media coverage on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/media-coverage/</link>
    <description>Recent content in media coverage on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 11:53:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/media-coverage/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Link between improvement of the environment and society?</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/link-between-improvement-of-the-environment-and-society/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 11:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/link-between-improvement-of-the-environment-and-society/</guid>
      <description>While I am aware of my tendency to discount anything older as 10 years as ancient in science terms, I do try to sketch a brief historical of each issue I discuss in (most of) my research articles. However, I am always surprised by the lack of &amp;ldquo;history&amp;rdquo; in quality reporting on scientific progress.&amp;nbsp;A recent story in Nature, &amp;ldquo;Can conservation cut poverty&amp;rdquo;, investigated the link between preserving biodiversity and positive influences this might have on the local inhabitants.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Translating research</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/translating-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 13:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/translating-research/</guid>
      <description>Amanda is currently trying to publish the first chapter of her thesis (whohoo), and this can do funny things to your brain. See the post on her personal blog on how research findings are translated through the different media outlets, or the scientific version of telephone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The latest Birdfish</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-latest-birdfish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2010 18:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-latest-birdfish/</guid>
      <description>The Churchill Northern Studies Centre has hosted researchers from the Cottenie lab for the past couple years. This year we were invited to contribute a short write-up on our summer 2009 field season. You can read the article here:
http://www.churchillscience.ca/documents/Newsletter_Winter_2010.pdf
Also, be sure to check out the CNSC&amp;rsquo;s website for a preview of their new facility! The staff and volunteers at the CNSC are very supportive and a terrific resource for anyone doing science in the north.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The planktoneers make headlines!</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-planktoneers-make-headlines/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2010 11:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-planktoneers-make-headlines/</guid>
      <description>We will participate as a lab to the species parade in Kitchener/Waterloo. Our theme? The planktoneers, of course. This seems not to be the most obvious theme, so we are mentioned in some of the local papers. As Ingrid wrote: &amp;ldquo;The heat is on&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>