<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>environmental philosophy on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/environmental-philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in environmental philosophy on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2010 09:13:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/environmental-philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>the L word</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-l-word/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2010 09:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-l-word/</guid>
      <description>If I could meet any person, dead or alive, real or fiction, I think one of my top choices would be Steve Irwin. I&amp;rsquo;d want to meet him out in the bush, maybe in Australia, maybe help him re-locate a croc. Afterwards, we might talk about conservation and peace and wilderness. Or, more accurately, he&amp;rsquo;d talk, and I&amp;rsquo;d just nod vigorously in agreement while reveling in his radiance.
Steve Irwin is famously known for his larger-than-life television series Crocodile Hunter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Empty Cups</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/empty-cups/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2010 14:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/empty-cups/</guid>
      <description>Very occasionally, I will brave North American culture and go see a movie on a ridiculously big screen with a ridiculously big bag of popcorn. Last December, a friend convinced me to not only go see Avatar on the big screen, but to watch it in 3-D with her. I was blown away. Though I find the current 3-D craze to be, well, crazy, I have to admit that it brought a certain enchantment to the fantasy planet Pandora.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecofeminism: not just tree-hugging and hairy legs</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/ecofeminism-not-just-tree-hugging-and-hairy-legs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2010 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/ecofeminism-not-just-tree-hugging-and-hairy-legs/</guid>
      <description>In March 2009, the Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies undergraduate program (among others) was cut at Guelph. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t involved in the issue myself, but knew a few people who rallied against this decision. They cited it as ironic evidence that feminism is far from being a finished movement. At the time, I only saw a superficial link between the Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies program cut and feminism; I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what feminism really was.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How much for that polar bear?</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/how-much-for-that-polar-bear/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2010 22:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/how-much-for-that-polar-bear/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;The federal government wants to put a price tag on polar bears,&amp;rdquo; begins this recent Globe and Mail article. It goes on to explain that Environment Canada wants to determine the socio-economic value of the iconic arctic species. This includes things like the bear&amp;rsquo;s consumptive value, cultural value, scientific value, educational value, aesthetic value, existence value, and so on. How much does each &amp;ldquo;additional unit of polar bear&amp;rdquo; or each &amp;ldquo;additional hectare of habitat&amp;rdquo; bring to the nation?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>