<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cottenie Lab on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cottenie Lab on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Priority effects of stream eutrophication and assembly history on beta diversity across aquatic consumers, decomposers and producers</title>
      <link>/publication/dunck-2021-sotte/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/dunck-2021-sotte/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Metacognitive Instructional Guide to Support Effective Studying Strategies</title>
      <link>/publication/bingham-2021-cjstl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/bingham-2021-cjstl/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining the effects of heterospecific abundance on dispersal in forest small mammals</title>
      <link>/publication/denomme-brown-2021-jom/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/denomme-brown-2021-jom/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>At each site its diversity: DNA barcoding reveals remarkable earthworm diversity in neotropical rainforests of French Guiana</title>
      <link>/publication/maggia-2021-ase/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/maggia-2021-ase/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reconciling seascape genetics and fisheries science in three codistributed flatfishes</title>
      <link>/publication/vandamme-2021-ea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/vandamme-2021-ea/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethanol eDNA Reveals Unique Community Composition of Aquatic Macroinvertebrates Compared to Bulk Tissue Metabarcoding in a Biomonitoring Sampling Scheme</title>
      <link>/publication/persaud-2021-d/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/persaud-2021-d/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Floods homogenize aquatic communities across time but not across space in a Neotropical floodplain</title>
      <link>/publication/petsch-2021-as/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/petsch-2021-as/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping and understanding the vulnerability of northern peatlands to permafrost thaw at scales relevant to community adaptation planning</title>
      <link>/publication/gibson-2021-erl/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/gibson-2021-erl/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatio-temporal analyses show conflicting evidence of the role of an invasive minnow in the decline of an endangered desert fish endemic to the south-western U.S.A.</title>
      <link>/publication/trombley-2021-fb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/trombley-2021-fb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variation in space and time: a long-term examination of density-dependent dispersal in a woodland rodent</title>
      <link>/publication/denomme-brown-2020-o/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/denomme-brown-2020-o/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessment of stream macroinvertebrate communities with eDNA is not congruent with tissue-based metabarcoding</title>
      <link>/publication/gleason-2020-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/gleason-2020-me/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transposable element persistence via potential genome-level ecosystem engineering</title>
      <link>/publication/kremer-2020-bg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/kremer-2020-bg/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Into the wild: microbiome transplant studies need broader ecological reality</title>
      <link>/publication/greyson-gaito-2020-potrsbbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/greyson-gaito-2020-potrsbbs/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bring your kid to work day</title>
      <link>/post/kids_at_work/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 10:17:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/kids_at_work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On November 5, it was bring your kid to work day for Grade 9 students. My oldest son (Kobe) wanted to participate, so I created a fun-packed (I thought) day for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highlight for him: siting in on Sho and Nick&amp;rsquo;s Biodiversity class. At dinner that evening, he could tell us all about what he learned in that class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lowlight for him: my biostats class. Hopefully I have not ruined statistics for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highlight for me: our time with Alex when he explained how he takes his gigapan pictures, seeing the fox den on campus, and that the name of the fencing company is Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;




  

&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/posts/kobe_kid_work.jpg&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;Kobe on campus&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metacommunity Workshop in Belem</title>
      <link>/post/metacommunity_workshop_belem/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 10:17:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/metacommunity_workshop_belem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I (Karl Cottenie) had a busy weeklong trip to Belem, Brazil, at the end of October. I was invited to facilitate a 2.5 day workshop, give a research seminar, and be part of an MSc qualifying defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://photos.app.goo.gl/XuEohRajuAoFb1p78&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for some pictures of my trip, and below is a little bit more information on what I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was really fun (and a lot of work) to put together the material for the metacommunity workshop. I did a lot of hands-on activities, where the participants performed a quick meta-analysis, explored metacommunity dynamics with a simple but powerful simulation model in R, and finally analysed the simulation results with the vegan package in R. This is the second time I have been in Brazil, and I have now advised several Brazilian PhD students, and I was again impressed by the quality of the Brazilian ecologists. Hopefully I will be able to continue my interactions with them, because I myself learned a lot during the 2.5 day workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research seminar was a first summary of the last 5 years of research from my lab on temporal metacommunity dynamics. Most of that research is currently submitted, resubmitted or almost ready to submit, so hopefully I will be able to share more of this exciting research soon here too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, Lucas Corales presented his MSc research progress. They gave an impressive presentation with stunning visuals, and the science behind it was equally impressive. I am looking forward to the publication that will come out of this research, and the rest of their carreer. Great things will come out of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you could get the impression that there was little time for fully enjoying Brazil, you are mistaken. In the downtime, I ate local foods (tacaca, jambu, peixada, acai icecream, cupuacu, muruci, taperaba), and visited the local rainforest (sort of).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is to hoping I will be able to go back there in the near future :-)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
