<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Brittany Jones on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/brittany-jones/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Brittany Jones on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 May 2012 10:02:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/brittany-jones/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Brittany defended yesterday...</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/brittany-defended-yesterday.../</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2012 10:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/brittany-defended-yesterday.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; successfully, of course. Now we just have to turn it into a publication. I always give a short speech during the celebrations afterwards, and the theme was what Brittany, her personality, brought to the research project (Ryan Gregory&amp;rsquo;s great standard question). She was much too modest when she answered this during her defence, so I answered it for her:
her organizational talents (keeping track of the extensive experiments and field observations, all at the same time)her efficient and hard work (she counted more than 600 samples one summer, compared to my 90+ samples for my entire PhD)her intellectual contributions to her thesis, which looks very straightforward afterward, but it took us many iterations to understand and explain it this clearlyknowing how to handle me (important one!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The battle of zooplankton</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-battle-of-zooplankton/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 16:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-battle-of-zooplankton/</guid>
      <description>Kaleigh Eichel, a student in Knowledge Integration, did research in Churchill for two summers. In addition to her research, she also created a web site translating some of the research in Churchill to the general public. One of the episodes features the projects done by Amanda and Brittany:
http://www.avioyak.ca/episode3.html&amp;nbsp;

Enjoy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Picture blog 2</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/picture-blog-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 11:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/picture-blog-2/</guid>
      <description>My old lab space.

New lab space. Much more organized.

H.arcticus for my first LC50.

The box I constructed to control the light for my LC50.

Inside the box.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brittany&#39;s first picture blog from the field</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/brittanys-first-picture-blog-from-the-field/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 17:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/brittanys-first-picture-blog-from-the-field/</guid>
      <description>Sunset on the train

First day exploring Bluff A with Celia and Shelley.

Putting the finishing touches on Celia&amp;rsquo;s mesocosms before we put them in the water.

The final product? Not quite&amp;hellip;for some reason they keep sinking. Still troubleshooting.

First day on Bluff D.

Shelley learning how we sample rock pools.

&amp;hellip;and of course my first polar bear sighting. Right outside the CNSC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brittany&#39;s first publication!</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/brittanys-first-publication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2011 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/brittanys-first-publication/</guid>
      <description>Brittany&amp;rsquo;s first publication stemming from her undergraduate research project during the Algonquin field course has just been published. She was part of team IDH (for obvious reasons), and they worked their butts of to collect the data: finding an interesting question based on her previous community ecology course, interviewing park people to find stands with known time-to-logging, collecting the data, tiring out the TAs who helped them (or maybe slowed them down), breaking down her field vehicle, of course exactly on the one day I came out with them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Field work is winding down in Churchill</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/field-work-is-winding-down-in-churchill/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2010 15:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/field-work-is-winding-down-in-churchill/</guid>
      <description>Mid august, and it is starting to feel like summer is indeed slowly winding down.
Amanda is also feeling signs ofFall in Churchill, and Brittany has just put an update about her first field season up there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More science outreach in Churchill</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/more-science-outreach-in-churchill/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 13:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/more-science-outreach-in-churchill/</guid>
      <description>see here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A preview</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/a-preview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2010 12:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/a-preview/</guid>
      <description>A preview of things to come in the subarctic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer 2010 fieldwork has begun!</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/summer-2010-fieldwork-has-begun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2010 23:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/summer-2010-fieldwork-has-begun/</guid>
      <description>The Cottenie lab will be active in Churchill, Manitoba again this year. I arrived in Churchill about a week ago and Brittany will be joining me in a few short weeks. Check out our progress as Planktoneers!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some pre fieldwork fieldwork</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/some-pre-fieldwork-fieldwork/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 22:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/some-pre-fieldwork-fieldwork/</guid>
      <description>Today Brittany and I took a walk over to the Arboretum to sample some of the temporary and man-made ponds, as part of an ongoing metacommunity study. With the warm spring we&amp;rsquo;ve been having, the zooplankton are in full swing, rivalling the communities we found in Churchill last year in August!Here Brittany is marvelling at the zooplankton and many aquatic insects:

Notice the tea-coloured water, it is stained by tannins leaching from the fallen leaves and detritus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are you? Zooplankton? Hahahahahahahaha.</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/what-are-you-zooplankton-hahahahahahahaha./</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2010 17:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/what-are-you-zooplankton-hahahahahahahaha./</guid>
      <description>After a whole month of preparations, it finally happened: the procession of species. It started a little bit late for us, since I had a race in the morning. But thanks to cell phones, we could join the parade half way through. Kobe was really excited and waiting for the first sign of the parade and the rest of the lab.
Here are some random pictures of the different species and musicians bringing life music.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More costumes</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/more-costumes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2010 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/more-costumes/</guid>
      <description>How many do you need to make a costume? Apparently more than 5. However, based on this last evening, we now have a full design, including the know-how on how to make it. So the next time we meet, we should have 6 full Daphnia costumes for the parade.&amp;nbsp;4 degrees to work with papier mache, your quality education at work
To illustrate that this is part of the rostrum, all you dirty minds&amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let the costumes begin!</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/let-the-costumes-begin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Mar 2010 10:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/let-the-costumes-begin/</guid>
      <description>Well, as Karl has mentioned our lab will be participating as a horde of zooplankton in the KW Procession of Species Parade. The parade is as much about encouragaing local expressions of art as it is about showcasing biodiversity. With that in mind we set out yesterday to stretch our creativity and construct a prototype of our first costume. We decided that Daphnia would be our main inspiration and started on a carapace and post abdomen.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>