<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>education on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>/tags/education/</link>
    <description>Recent content in education on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 11:29:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/education/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Making the story whole again</title>
      <link>/post/making-the-story-whole-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 11:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/making-the-story-whole-again/</guid>
      <description>Ingrid is featured in theAt Guelph! &amp;nbsp;I repeat, Ingrid is featured in the At Guelph! It is not her whole story, of course, but it does provide key aspects of her story.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three words, a world of difference</title>
      <link>/post/three-words-a-world-of-difference/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2011 11:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/three-words-a-world-of-difference/</guid>
      <description>I am teaching a field course in Algonquin this summer, and I &amp;ldquo;stress&amp;rdquo;, i.e. grade, two components of field work during this course: a group science project, and an individual natural history project. So the distinction (and similarities) between qualitative and quantitative are on the forefront of mind. This if, of course, compounded by Ingrid who will bring the qualitative approach into the hypothetico-deductive, quantitative, bastion that Integrative Biology is, after years of being exposed to Tom Nudds&amp;rsquo;s beating the bush ;-)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Soap box</title>
      <link>/post/soap-box/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2011 10:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/soap-box/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes I like it when Margaret Wente gets on her soap box. She has a couple of recurring themes, and our university education system is one she uses every couple of months.Here is her latest, and I will have to do some counting on the issues she brings up, and comparing them to my own, personal, experiences:

&amp;ldquo;&amp;nbsp;A large number of students learn little or nothing in university. More than a third show no improvement in their skills at all.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecofeminism: not just tree-hugging and hairy legs</title>
      <link>/post/ecofeminism-not-just-tree-hugging-and-hairy-legs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2010 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/ecofeminism-not-just-tree-hugging-and-hairy-legs/</guid>
      <description>In March 2009, the Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies undergraduate program (among others) was cut at Guelph. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t involved in the issue myself, but knew a few people who rallied against this decision. They cited it as ironic evidence that feminism is far from being a finished movement. At the time, I only saw a superficial link between the Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies program cut and feminism; I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what feminism really was.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are our kids ready for neoliberal education? Absolutely!</title>
      <link>/post/are-our-kids-ready-for-neoliberal-education-absolutely/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2010 12:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/are-our-kids-ready-for-neoliberal-education-absolutely/</guid>
      <description>Teaching a course is a lot of fun. The difficult part is to convert all these highbrow ideas to a group of 22-year old &amp;ldquo;kids&amp;rdquo; at 8:30 am in the morning. I really like the concept of serendipity (or is this just a justification for being glued to Google Reader and my new RSS feeds), but I stumbled across this blog post at the beginning of the semester: Are our kids ready for this?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making group work bearable</title>
      <link>/post/making-group-work-bearable/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2010 23:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/making-group-work-bearable/</guid>
      <description>As an undergraduate, I always dreaded group work. Being an introvert, I always preferred to do things on my own, especially when I didn&amp;rsquo;t know my group members. The first phase of group work is the worst (in my opinion)&amp;ndash;getting to know each other and revealing our egos. Who are these people? Do you like them? Can you work with them? Do you connect, or exist on completely different planes?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Critical thinking and concept maps: a powerful combination</title>
      <link>/post/critical-thinking-and-concept-maps-a-powerful-combination/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2010 10:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/critical-thinking-and-concept-maps-a-powerful-combination/</guid>
      <description>Infographic by College Scholarships.org</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The most important piece of advice?</title>
      <link>/post/the-most-important-piece-of-advice/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 12:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-most-important-piece-of-advice/</guid>
      <description>Here is a great post, over on ProfHacker, about advice to new grad students: An open letter to new graduate students, by Brian Croxall.&amp;nbsp;While I agree with most of these topics with varying degrees, they did not include the most important piece of advise, probably because it is so obvious: ask questions. Our role as advisors is to advise, but we can only do this if we get questions. Come in my office, send me an email, skype, whatever.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Critical thinking: different perspectives</title>
      <link>/post/critical-thinking-different-perspectives/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jul 2010 12:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/critical-thinking-different-perspectives/</guid>
      <description>When we were preparing the grading rubric to assess critical thinking (which is more complicated than you might think), Marianne Staempfli found this very useful resource: The Critical Thinking Community.&amp;nbsp;While the website itself is&amp;nbsp;quaintly old-fashioned, it has a lot of useful information. For instance, a definition:
Critical thinking is the intellectually disciplined process of actively and skillfully conceptualizing, applying, analyzing, synthesizing, and/or evaluating information gathered from, or generated by, observation, experience, reflection, reasoning, or communication, as a guide to belief and action.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Concept maps: THE tool for learners?</title>
      <link>/post/concept-maps-the-tool-for-learners/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 11:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/concept-maps-the-tool-for-learners/</guid>
      <description>Learning (be it as a scientist, a teacher, a student, or any combination of the above, this will be the topic of another blog) is a difficult process, as any scientist, teacher, or student will tell you. However, sometimes you get struck by lightening, by an experience that makes you wonder, &amp;ldquo;How did I ever function without this?&amp;rdquo;. 3 years ago, I was introduced to concept mapping by Steve Crawford, but I am not exactly sure how we got on this subject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grade inflation excess</title>
      <link>/post/grade-inflation-excess/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jun 2010 11:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/grade-inflation-excess/</guid>
      <description>Where did it go wrong with our university system? One possible reason is the increasing importance of &#34;grades&#34; in the mind of a student, instructor, granting agency, employer, for the easy quantification it provides of a student&#39;s learning. This is problematic on so many different levels. Maybe the most important level is that education/teaching/learning is not about&amp;nbsp;&#34;to distinguish the wheat from the chaff&#34;,&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;but actually about learning. At Guelph, our guiding principle for teaching and learning is &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sub-arctic outreach</title>
      <link>/post/sub-arctic-outreach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jun 2010 13:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sub-arctic-outreach/</guid>
      <description>Is it possible that grade 3 kids are more interested in zooplankton than 3year university students? Click here to find out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out with rote learning</title>
      <link>/post/out-with-rote-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2010 10:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/out-with-rote-learning/</guid>
      <description>Tom Nudds and I co-taught community ecology for the first time together last semester (and Amanda was one of our wonderful TAs). Despite our differences ;-), we share a very similar teaching philosophy. And as a result of some crazy ideas, we decided to completely remodel community ecology. Tom&amp;rsquo;s rallying cry:
Out with rote learningTo implement this, we cut out all &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; aspects of grading in our course, and instead we implemented 3 research projects in a problem-based learning framework.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypotheses or data first - Update</title>
      <link>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2010 12:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first-update/</guid>
      <description>We discussed these two articles mentioned in a previous post in our Community Ecology class, and this is the summary of the very interesting discussion between the students, the TAs, and Tom and I:
It is not one or the other (which is actually acknowledges by using the &amp;ldquo;first&amp;rdquo; in the title)The scientific method is cyclical and depends on data, hypotheses, predictions, increased information, or is cyclical as is illustrated by TomBut I added (which was not supported by the majority of the students, or Tom ;-) that the start of the scientific method is data, or the description of a natural phenomenonI also tried to argue that the &amp;ldquo;hypotheses first&amp;rdquo; in its extreme is related to religion, since religion is essentially a hypothesis (causal mechanism) without data to support it, but at this point I was way outside my zone of expertise</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>