<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marina Neytcheva on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/marina-neytcheva/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Marina Neytcheva on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2011 07:48:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/marina-neytcheva/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Marina featured in the At Guelph</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/marina-featured-in-the-at-guelph/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2011 07:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/marina-featured-in-the-at-guelph/</guid>
      <description>http://atguelph.uoguelph.ca/2011/10/research-aims-to-understand-plant-extinction/</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marina&#39;s Vanier Award</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/marinas-vanier-award/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2011 11:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/marinas-vanier-award/</guid>
      <description>It is finally official, Marina&amp;rsquo;s Vanier Award has been made public, and I can finally boast about it. 1 out of the top 167 PhD students across natural, social, and medical sciences at the Canadian level is very impressive. Congratulations, Marina.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Showcase of Let&#39;s Talk Microbes</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/showcase-of-lets-talk-microbes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2011 09:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/showcase-of-lets-talk-microbes/</guid>
      <description>Last November, Marina and Amanda went to Kobe&amp;rsquo;s school to givea hands-on demonstration of microbes. The science teacher who invited them then nominated their activity to the Let&amp;rsquo;s Talk Science CIHR-Synapse award, a national competition. And they were selected as one of the 4 best showcase activities! And in the accompanying picture, you can see Amanda, Marina in the background, and my son Kobe with the spiderman sweater. How cool is all that?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s talk ... microbes</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/lets-talk-...-microbes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2010 12:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/lets-talk-...-microbes/</guid>
      <description>Amanda and Marina created a module to introduce Grade 1 kids to microbes for the programLet&amp;rsquo;s talk science. They picked a very challenging subject to introduce something we cannot see to 6 year-olds. However, they pulled it off very successfully using pictures, glow-in-the-dark powder and black lights, and a couple of microscope. I joined them for the final presentation (in my son&amp;rsquo;s class), and these are the pictures I took.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Field trip Carolinian forests</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/field-trip-carolinian-forests/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2010 18:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/field-trip-carolinian-forests/</guid>
      <description>In September, Marina will join our lab. She will study spatial patterns and metacommunity dynamics in Carolinian forest understory plants, and Andrew MacDougall is her co-advisor (since obviously I know nothing about plants). Today we visited 2 forest fragments, just to get an idea on the spatial (and temporal) scales of heterogeneity, and to get an idea of the practical considerations that drive the development of a research program.
The first set of pictures are some overviews of the different landscapes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>