<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>outreach on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/outreach/</link>
    <description>Recent content in outreach on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 10:17:17 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/outreach/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Bring your kid to work day</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/kids_at_work/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 10:17:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/kids_at_work/</guid>
      <description>On November 5, it was bring your kid to work day for Grade 9 students. My oldest son (Kobe) wanted to participate, so I created a fun-packed (I thought) day for him.
The highlight for him: siting in on Sho and Nick&amp;rsquo;s Biodiversity class. At dinner that evening, he could tell us all about what he learned in that class.
The lowlight for him: my biostats class. Hopefully I have not ruined statistics for him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Showcase of Let&#39;s Talk Microbes</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/showcase-of-lets-talk-microbes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2011 09:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/showcase-of-lets-talk-microbes/</guid>
      <description>Last November, Marina and Amanda went to Kobe&amp;rsquo;s school to givea hands-on demonstration of microbes. The science teacher who invited them then nominated their activity to the Let&amp;rsquo;s Talk Science CIHR-Synapse award, a national competition. And they were selected as one of the 4 best showcase activities! And in the accompanying picture, you can see Amanda, Marina in the background, and my son Kobe with the spiderman sweater. How cool is all that?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making science matter</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/making-science-matter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 19:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/making-science-matter/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I found myself eavesdropping on two elderly fellows debating an age-old question: does size matter? Yes! declared one. Small ones have never satisfied anyone. It needs to be big!You’ve got it all wrong,countered the other. Proper use of a small one can be just as good as having a big one. And what good is a big one if you don’t use it properly?/o:pIn a nearby lecture theatre the Costa-Rican Mermaid was preaching the power of long distance swimming to promote big ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s talk ... microbes</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/lets-talk-...-microbes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2010 12:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/lets-talk-...-microbes/</guid>
      <description>Amanda and Marina created a module to introduce Grade 1 kids to microbes for the programLet&amp;rsquo;s talk science. They picked a very challenging subject to introduce something we cannot see to 6 year-olds. However, they pulled it off very successfully using pictures, glow-in-the-dark powder and black lights, and a couple of microscope. I joined them for the final presentation (in my son&amp;rsquo;s class), and these are the pictures I took.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bike Lessons</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/bike-lessons/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 19:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/bike-lessons/</guid>
      <description>I am Ingrid, a returning member of the Cottenie lab. This is my first post, and it comes at one of those in-between times in my life. I am in between finishing a two-month bike tour and starting a three- (or four, or more&amp;hellip;?) year PhD. It&amp;rsquo;s been an interesting process, returning from the tour and re-integrating back into society.
First, a little about the tour. It was one of the best and most challenging things I have ever done.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More science outreach in Churchill</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/more-science-outreach-in-churchill/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 13:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/more-science-outreach-in-churchill/</guid>
      <description>see here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The scientific method: from intuition to data and back</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-scientific-method-from-intuition-to-data-and-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2010 12:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-scientific-method-from-intuition-to-data-and-back/</guid>
      <description>This is an article in the Globe and Mail that struck a cord with me,&amp;nbsp;&#34;Ten years that shook, rattled, rolled and helped repair the world&#34;&amp;nbsp;by Doug Saunders. If you do not have the time to read the full article, you can click on this shortened version with most of the salient points summarized in a concept map structure (make sure to click on it to see the bigger version so that you can actually read the text ;-):This article provides a very nice example of the&amp;nbsp;10th Cottenie Commandment: Thou Shalt Listen to thy Intuition, but Follow the Data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sub-arctic outreach</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/sub-arctic-outreach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jun 2010 13:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/sub-arctic-outreach/</guid>
      <description>Is it possible that grade 3 kids are more interested in zooplankton than 3year university students? Click here to find out.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>