<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>teaching and learning on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/teaching-and-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in teaching and learning on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 May 2017 09:27:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/teaching-and-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Students learn the most from each other</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/students-learn-the-most-from-each-other/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2017 09:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/students-learn-the-most-from-each-other/</guid>
      <description>This is something we have known for the last 10 years (or 20) through for instance the research done by Eric Mazur and collaborators.They showed that using peer instruction improved student learning of physics concepts by 20% in a real-world, class setting, compared to a &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; lecture-based approach with the sage on the stage imparting their wisdom to the young susceptible minds!
That is a fine example of a very deliberate teaching practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The magic board</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-magic-board/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2016 13:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-magic-board/</guid>
      <description>I have extolled the virtue of my whiteboard in previous posts (see e.g., here and here), but it turns out that knowing how to work with a whiteboard could actually get you a job. I often say that I am a believer in technology, that it will fix a lot of problems at several scales. Sometimes the best technology, though, is an old-school magic board and markers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>For the love of whiteboard</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/for-the-love-of-whiteboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2012 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/for-the-love-of-whiteboard/</guid>
      <description>Here is another convert of the magic of the whiteboard: http://lifehacker.com/5950957/how-a-whiteboard-helped-a-terrible-delegator-keep-a-team-on+task.
He provides a list of why whiteboards work:
&amp;ldquo;Whiteboards are big enough for everybody to see.Whiteboards make you want to fill the space, and therefore expand and branch your thoughts.Whiteboards inspire you to keep writing, to keep pushing on what&amp;rsquo;s in your head, because it feels awesome to swing your arms that widely.&amp;nbsp;Whiteboards feel less like you&amp;rsquo;re committing to an idea than throwing it out for consideration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inspirational stories for teachers</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/inspirational-stories-for-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2012 08:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/inspirational-stories-for-teachers/</guid>
      <description>An oldie, but worthy of a link:&amp;nbsp;http://blogs.plos.org/neurotribes/2011/10/05/whats-the-most-important-lesson-you-learned-from-a-teacher/
I have since tried to identify a specific teacher and lesson for my own story, but I am not good at recalling memories, and my university teachers were pretty old school, sage-on-the-stage types of teachers, not exactly my style.
The one person that keeps coming up is my first kayak instructor (name forgotten) when I was 16 (?), in France. It was just me and him, and he really focused on breaking kayaking down the basics: reading the water (currents and countercurrents) and weight position in the boat (left-right and front-back), followed by exercises that internalized those basics before moving to the next step.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>End of semester</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/end-of-semester/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2012 15:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/end-of-semester/</guid>
      <description>I am about to submit the grades for the two courses this semester, and this often leads to self reflection. I am not going to do that now, but I will do something better: link to the self reflection of a teacher that is well-written, funny, insightful, sometimes reflects my own experiences, sometimes not at all. So I highly recommend William Bowers&amp;rsquo; &amp;ldquo;All we read is freaks&amp;rdquo;&amp;nbsp;for all educators.
I could extract so many passages out of this long piece, but this is the one I emailed to myself:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discussing place-based education ...</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/discussing-place-based-education-.../</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2012 16:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/discussing-place-based-education-.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; outside in the Arboretum, with our First Year Seminar class. The (only?) advantage of an early spring this year.

Although Ingrid would probably point out that our discussions, even in the Arboretum,
&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip; had been sitting on the land, instead of having roots within&amp;nbsp;it.&amp;rdquo; (Laura Piersol, Canadian Journal of Environmental Education, 2010, 15:198-209)But how to design a university course to have its roots within the land? It is easier to do this in the context of a field course, but with a Monday-Wednesday 8:30-10 am lecture slot?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The fallacy of our misunderstand of the scientific method</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-fallacy-of-our-misunderstand-of-the-scientific-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2012 11:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-fallacy-of-our-misunderstand-of-the-scientific-method/</guid>
      <description>Ryan Norris via Tom Nudds sent me a link to this web site, and I think all three of us had the same &amp;ldquo;What the &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; reaction after reading the entry by Irene Pepperberg, titled &amp;ldquo;The Fallacy of Hypothesis Testing&amp;rdquo;:
&amp;ldquo;I was trained, as a chemist, to use the classic scientific method: Devise a testable hypothesis, and then design an experiment to see if the hypothesis is correct or not. And I was told that this method is equally valid for the social sciences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientific debate...</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/scientific-debate.../</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2012 12:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/scientific-debate.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; rests on actually reading and understanding each other&amp;rsquo;s words.
This is a difficult exercise, and not only for students. Tom Nudds and I just covered in community ecology the rationale for protected areas planning based not only on representativeness (making sure that all species are protected), but more importantly also on persistence (see his article in Biodiversity and Conservation for a summary of their ideas). If the target areas have all the species you want to conserve, but lack essential components that would ensure their actual persistence through time, representativeness means nothing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Context is everything</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/context-is-everything/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 10:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/context-is-everything/</guid>
      <description>An interesting paper in Science by Stumpf and Porter&amp;nbsp;takes a hard look at &amp;ldquo;general&amp;rdquo; power laws in science:
&amp;ldquo;A striking feature that has attracted considerable attention is the apparent ubiquity of power-law relationships in empirical data. However, although power laws have been reported in areas ranging from finance and molecular biology to geophysics and the Internet, the data are typically insufficient and the mechanistic insights are almost always too limited for the identification of power-law behavior to be scientifically useful (see the figure).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tangled bank</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/tangled-bank/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2012 08:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/tangled-bank/</guid>
      <description>What do these four, apparently very unconnected items, have in common?
&amp;nbsp;http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2012/02/lake-vostok-drilled/
http://www.thecleanestline.com/2012/02/cerro-torre-deviations-from-reason.htmlStar wars: the clone wars
http://www.vpacademic.uoguelph.ca/fys/seminars/My life used to be easy.
I was a scientist,&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;climber (a long time ago),&amp;nbsp;father, and a&amp;nbsp;teacher. And now suddenly these separate aspects of &amp;nbsp;my life got sucked into a vortex, all thanks to reading some passages of Aldo Leopold&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Land Ethic&amp;rdquo; for the First Year Seminar course Ingrid and I have designed.&amp;nbsp;These items literally came across my desk (RSS reader, watching TV with the kids, teaching a course) in a 2 day period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connecting dots when running in the morning</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/connecting-dots-when-running-in-the-morning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 13:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/connecting-dots-when-running-in-the-morning/</guid>
      <description>The joy of running for me, in addition to spending quality time with the kids, is theidle time it offers me. My mind wonders off, and connects several dots that are floating around in my brain.
One of these dots is this image I mentioned before.&amp;nbsp;I mentioned that creating a process to move student from the first behaviour to the second was difficult.

Another dot is why I like Moksha yoga, but could not be bothered at all by Bikram yoga.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Definition of teaching</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/definition-of-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2011 10:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/definition-of-teaching/</guid>
      <description>I could not resist posting this cartoon. It defines what teaching is: creating a process that moves a learner from the left-hand circle to the right-hand circle, nothing more, nothing less. Creating that process efficiently and effectively, however, is of course a completely different question.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another inspirational video</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/another-inspirational-video/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2010 11:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/another-inspirational-video/</guid>
      <description>This video touches all my buttons: teaching, education, collaboration, comics, story telling, science, humor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s talk ... microbes</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/lets-talk-...-microbes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2010 12:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/lets-talk-...-microbes/</guid>
      <description>Amanda and Marina created a module to introduce Grade 1 kids to microbes for the programLet&amp;rsquo;s talk science. They picked a very challenging subject to introduce something we cannot see to 6 year-olds. However, they pulled it off very successfully using pictures, glow-in-the-dark powder and black lights, and a couple of microscope. I joined them for the final presentation (in my son&amp;rsquo;s class), and these are the pictures I took.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reduce &#43; Simplify &#43; Deepen &#43; collaboration</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/reduce-simplify-deepen-collaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Nov 2010 13:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/reduce-simplify-deepen-collaboration/</guid>
      <description>Creating a concept map as a teaching/learning tool is all about what Chris Orwig refers to when he describes the poetics of pictures: it is not only about reducing and simplifying, but also (especially) about deepening (or synthesis in teaching terms). It is this last part that makes it very difficult, and rewarding. And to make this deepening work, it is all about dialogue and collaboration, which is why I believe that class room interactions are crucial in this day and age of moving more and more to digital interactions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are our kids ready for neoliberal education? Absolutely!</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/are-our-kids-ready-for-neoliberal-education-absolutely/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2010 12:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/are-our-kids-ready-for-neoliberal-education-absolutely/</guid>
      <description>Teaching a course is a lot of fun. The difficult part is to convert all these highbrow ideas to a group of 22-year old &amp;ldquo;kids&amp;rdquo; at 8:30 am in the morning. I really like the concept of serendipity (or is this just a justification for being glued to Google Reader and my new RSS feeds), but I stumbled across this blog post at the beginning of the semester: Are our kids ready for this?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making group work bearable</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/making-group-work-bearable/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2010 23:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/making-group-work-bearable/</guid>
      <description>As an undergraduate, I always dreaded group work. Being an introvert, I always preferred to do things on my own, especially when I didn&amp;rsquo;t know my group members. The first phase of group work is the worst (in my opinion)&amp;ndash;getting to know each other and revealing our egos. Who are these people? Do you like them? Can you work with them? Do you connect, or exist on completely different planes?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>