<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Churchill on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>/tags/churchill/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Churchill on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 May 2012 10:02:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/churchill/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Brittany defended yesterday...</title>
      <link>/post/brittany-defended-yesterday.../</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2012 10:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/brittany-defended-yesterday.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; successfully, of course. Now we just have to turn it into a publication. I always give a short speech during the celebrations afterwards, and the theme was what Brittany, her personality, brought to the research project (Ryan Gregory&amp;rsquo;s great standard question). She was much too modest when she answered this during her defence, so I answered it for her:
her organizational talents (keeping track of the extensive experiments and field observations, all at the same time)her efficient and hard work (she counted more than 600 samples one summer, compared to my 90+ samples for my entire PhD)her intellectual contributions to her thesis, which looks very straightforward afterward, but it took us many iterations to understand and explain it this clearlyknowing how to handle me (important one!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Picture blog 2</title>
      <link>/post/picture-blog-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 11:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/picture-blog-2/</guid>
      <description>My old lab space.

New lab space. Much more organized.

H.arcticus for my first LC50.

The box I constructed to control the light for my LC50.

Inside the box.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polar bears gone wild.</title>
      <link>/post/polar-bears-gone-wild./</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2011 11:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/polar-bears-gone-wild./</guid>
      <description>Doing research in Churchill is not without its perils: sleep deprivation, bugs, road rage, and polar bears. Brittany said it was a slow season so far, but not every bear read the memo: see this CBC article on a polar bear gone wild.&amp;nbsp;
All joking aside, sadly enough when wildlife goes wild, the consequences for the animal in question are much more severe than an&amp;nbsp;embarrassing Youtube video.
From the original CBC article: notice the person behind the rock, a little to the left of the hind legs!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brittany&#39;s first picture blog from the field</title>
      <link>/post/brittanys-first-picture-blog-from-the-field/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 17:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/brittanys-first-picture-blog-from-the-field/</guid>
      <description>Sunset on the train

First day exploring Bluff A with Celia and Shelley.

Putting the finishing touches on Celia&amp;rsquo;s mesocosms before we put them in the water.

The final product? Not quite&amp;hellip;for some reason they keep sinking. Still troubleshooting.

First day on Bluff D.

Shelley learning how we sample rock pools.

&amp;hellip;and of course my first polar bear sighting. Right outside the CNSC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Latest summary of Churchill Research</title>
      <link>/post/latest-summary-of-churchill-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2010 06:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/latest-summary-of-churchill-research/</guid>
      <description>I recently gave a presentation at the University of Toronto - Mississauga, and that was the perfect opportunity to summarize the research results from our lab in Churchill of the last couple of years. Below you can see the slides of that presentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scaling up</title>
      <link>/post/scaling-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2010 16:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/scaling-up/</guid>
      <description>In our lab, we focus mainly on metacommunity dynamics, or how the interactions between dispersal and local environmental processes influence communities in the landscape. Since we are interested in communities in the landscape, we automatically deal with the issue of &amp;ldquo;scale&amp;rdquo;. This is one of those very diffuse concepts in ecology, with as many definitions as scientists (temporal, spatial, conceptual, grain, &amp;hellip;).
This&amp;nbsp;recent article by Spivak et al. in Freshwater Biology&amp;nbsp;tackles a problem experimentally that is not often studied in ecology: how applicable are the results of small-scale experiments for empirical (and by default large-scale) systems?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confessions of a grad student</title>
      <link>/post/confessions-of-a-grad-student/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2010 11:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/confessions-of-a-grad-student/</guid>
      <description>Are you intrigued by these snippets?I like statsI dislike learning R&amp;nbsp;results may be meaninglessTedious? Yes. Accurate? Yes&amp;nbsp;Then go over to&amp;nbsp;Amanda&#39;s latest blog post.&amp;nbsp; </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientists measure...</title>
      <link>/post/scientists-measure.../</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2010 15:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/scientists-measure.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; all kinds of things. See Amanda&amp;rsquo;s latest post from Churchill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Field work is winding down in Churchill</title>
      <link>/post/field-work-is-winding-down-in-churchill/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2010 15:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/field-work-is-winding-down-in-churchill/</guid>
      <description>Mid august, and it is starting to feel like summer is indeed slowly winding down.
Amanda is also feeling signs ofFall in Churchill, and Brittany has just put an update about her first field season up there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More science outreach in Churchill</title>
      <link>/post/more-science-outreach-in-churchill/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 13:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/more-science-outreach-in-churchill/</guid>
      <description>see here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A preview</title>
      <link>/post/a-preview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2010 12:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/a-preview/</guid>
      <description>A preview of things to come in the subarctic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amanda&#39;s hatching experiment</title>
      <link>/post/amandas-hatching-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2010 09:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/amandas-hatching-experiment/</guid>
      <description>Ecology in action, life, in Churchill, with pictures, and explanations, using the magic of tupperware. Who said science is boring and expensive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sub-arctic outreach</title>
      <link>/post/sub-arctic-outreach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jun 2010 13:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sub-arctic-outreach/</guid>
      <description>Is it possible that grade 3 kids are more interested in zooplankton than 3year university students? Click here to find out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amanda&#39;s first blog post of the season</title>
      <link>/post/amandas-first-blog-post-of-the-season/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2010 13:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/amandas-first-blog-post-of-the-season/</guid>
      <description>about trains, plains, and canoes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer 2010 fieldwork has begun!</title>
      <link>/post/summer-2010-fieldwork-has-begun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2010 23:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/summer-2010-fieldwork-has-begun/</guid>
      <description>The Cottenie lab will be active in Churchill, Manitoba again this year. I arrived in Churchill about a week ago and Brittany will be joining me in a few short weeks. Check out our progress as Planktoneers!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The world of conferences</title>
      <link>/post/the-world-of-conferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2010 16:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-world-of-conferences/</guid>
      <description>I also had the opportunity to attend a conference this week, the 5th annual meeting of the Canadian Society for Ecology and Evolution, held at the Universite Laval. It was a well organized conference with a lot of energy and some very interesting talks and posters. Quebec City served as a wonderful setting for the conference and I was impressed by how the conference was truly bilingual. I was also impressed by vieux Quebec and the beauty of the St.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>