<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>critical thinking on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>/tags/critical-thinking/</link>
    <description>Recent content in critical thinking on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2012 08:24:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/critical-thinking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tangled bank</title>
      <link>/post/tangled-bank/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2012 08:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tangled-bank/</guid>
      <description>What do these four, apparently very unconnected items, have in common?
&amp;nbsp;http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2012/02/lake-vostok-drilled/
http://www.thecleanestline.com/2012/02/cerro-torre-deviations-from-reason.htmlStar wars: the clone wars
http://www.vpacademic.uoguelph.ca/fys/seminars/My life used to be easy.
I was a scientist,&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;climber (a long time ago),&amp;nbsp;father, and a&amp;nbsp;teacher. And now suddenly these separate aspects of &amp;nbsp;my life got sucked into a vortex, all thanks to reading some passages of Aldo Leopold&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Land Ethic&amp;rdquo; for the First Year Seminar course Ingrid and I have designed.&amp;nbsp;These items literally came across my desk (RSS reader, watching TV with the kids, teaching a course) in a 2 day period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abstraction - or making explicit connections</title>
      <link>/post/abstraction-or-making-explicit-connections/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2011 14:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/abstraction-or-making-explicit-connections/</guid>
      <description>One of the items in the grading rubric Marianne Staempfli and I developed for concept maps is the importance of cross links in the arrangement of the concept map:
&amp;ldquo;Cross links show complex relationships between two or more distinct segments of the concept map&amp;rdquo;It is one of the reasons why I am currently involved in a collaboration (among some others) on genome (or transposon) ecology by co-advising Brent Saylor with Ryan Gregory, and on anthropology in ecology by co-advising Ingrid Ng with Bob Jickling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The importance of constraints</title>
      <link>/post/the-importance-of-constraints/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 16:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-importance-of-constraints/</guid>
      <description>For me, one of the biggest mysteries of the scientific method (see e.g. this post), is that it provides such a rigid structure, yet at the same time so creative. It turns out that constraints actually lead to more global, conceptual, and maybe thus more creative thinking.Jonah Lehrer in Wired provides some excellent context for a recent study that investigated this link explicitly. Highly recommended.
At the same time, this could also explain one of my other pet peeves: why concept mapping is such a powerful method.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Link between improvement of the environment and society?</title>
      <link>/post/link-between-improvement-of-the-environment-and-society/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 11:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/link-between-improvement-of-the-environment-and-society/</guid>
      <description>While I am aware of my tendency to discount anything older as 10 years as ancient in science terms, I do try to sketch a brief historical of each issue I discuss in (most of) my research articles. However, I am always surprised by the lack of &amp;ldquo;history&amp;rdquo; in quality reporting on scientific progress.&amp;nbsp;A recent story in Nature, &amp;ldquo;Can conservation cut poverty&amp;rdquo;, investigated the link between preserving biodiversity and positive influences this might have on the local inhabitants.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another inspirational video</title>
      <link>/post/another-inspirational-video/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2010 11:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/another-inspirational-video/</guid>
      <description>This video touches all my buttons: teaching, education, collaboration, comics, story telling, science, humor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reduce &#43; Simplify &#43; Deepen &#43; collaboration</title>
      <link>/post/reduce-simplify-deepen-collaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Nov 2010 13:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/reduce-simplify-deepen-collaboration/</guid>
      <description>Creating a concept map as a teaching/learning tool is all about what Chris Orwig refers to when he describes the poetics of pictures: it is not only about reducing and simplifying, but also (especially) about deepening (or synthesis in teaching terms). It is this last part that makes it very difficult, and rewarding. And to make this deepening work, it is all about dialogue and collaboration, which is why I believe that class room interactions are crucial in this day and age of moving more and more to digital interactions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecofeminism: not just tree-hugging and hairy legs</title>
      <link>/post/ecofeminism-not-just-tree-hugging-and-hairy-legs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2010 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/ecofeminism-not-just-tree-hugging-and-hairy-legs/</guid>
      <description>In March 2009, the Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies undergraduate program (among others) was cut at Guelph. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t involved in the issue myself, but knew a few people who rallied against this decision. They cited it as ironic evidence that feminism is far from being a finished movement. At the time, I only saw a superficial link between the Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies program cut and feminism; I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what feminism really was.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Critical thinking and concept maps: a powerful combination</title>
      <link>/post/critical-thinking-and-concept-maps-a-powerful-combination/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2010 10:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/critical-thinking-and-concept-maps-a-powerful-combination/</guid>
      <description>Infographic by College Scholarships.org</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The power of graphics</title>
      <link>/post/the-power-of-graphics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2010 16:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-power-of-graphics/</guid>
      <description>Intelligent persons have written wonderful books about creating good graphs. Today, I received two graphs in my Google Reader, and they make such powerful/funny statements that I had to show them, especially since they are visually so comparable.
In the funny category:

In the powerful category (click here for the original article with more powerful visuals):

It&amp;rsquo;s very unlikely that anything in my research career will produce anything that funny, or could influence the voting behaviour of a whole nation, but we can only try.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The most important piece of advice?</title>
      <link>/post/the-most-important-piece-of-advice/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 12:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-most-important-piece-of-advice/</guid>
      <description>Here is a great post, over on ProfHacker, about advice to new grad students: An open letter to new graduate students, by Brian Croxall.&amp;nbsp;While I agree with most of these topics with varying degrees, they did not include the most important piece of advise, probably because it is so obvious: ask questions. Our role as advisors is to advise, but we can only do this if we get questions. Come in my office, send me an email, skype, whatever.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Critical thinking: different perspectives</title>
      <link>/post/critical-thinking-different-perspectives/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jul 2010 12:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/critical-thinking-different-perspectives/</guid>
      <description>When we were preparing the grading rubric to assess critical thinking (which is more complicated than you might think), Marianne Staempfli found this very useful resource: The Critical Thinking Community.&amp;nbsp;While the website itself is&amp;nbsp;quaintly old-fashioned, it has a lot of useful information. For instance, a definition:
Critical thinking is the intellectually disciplined process of actively and skillfully conceptualizing, applying, analyzing, synthesizing, and/or evaluating information gathered from, or generated by, observation, experience, reflection, reasoning, or communication, as a guide to belief and action.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The scientific method: from intuition to data and back</title>
      <link>/post/the-scientific-method-from-intuition-to-data-and-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2010 12:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-scientific-method-from-intuition-to-data-and-back/</guid>
      <description>This is an article in the Globe and Mail that struck a cord with me,&amp;nbsp;&#34;Ten years that shook, rattled, rolled and helped repair the world&#34;&amp;nbsp;by Doug Saunders. If you do not have the time to read the full article, you can click on this shortened version with most of the salient points summarized in a concept map structure (make sure to click on it to see the bigger version so that you can actually read the text ;-):This article provides a very nice example of the&amp;nbsp;10th Cottenie Commandment: Thou Shalt Listen to thy Intuition, but Follow the Data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypotheses or data first? Update 2</title>
      <link>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first-update-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 15:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first-update-2/</guid>
      <description>Since we seem to be on a roll on the what should come first in science, this Nature article actually presents a much better written and argued case in favour of combining the strengths of both approaches (maybe scientists should do what they are good at, science, and leave the writing to, journalists with a PhD?). Some of the costs for doing these genome studies: US$1 billion. How does that stack up to other funding, I have no idea, but this is a big number.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypotheses or data first - Update</title>
      <link>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2010 12:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first-update/</guid>
      <description>We discussed these two articles mentioned in a previous post in our Community Ecology class, and this is the summary of the very interesting discussion between the students, the TAs, and Tom and I:
It is not one or the other (which is actually acknowledges by using the &amp;ldquo;first&amp;rdquo; in the title)The scientific method is cyclical and depends on data, hypotheses, predictions, increased information, or is cyclical as is illustrated by TomBut I added (which was not supported by the majority of the students, or Tom ;-) that the start of the scientific method is data, or the description of a natural phenomenonI also tried to argue that the &amp;ldquo;hypotheses first&amp;rdquo; in its extreme is related to religion, since religion is essentially a hypothesis (causal mechanism) without data to support it, but at this point I was way outside my zone of expertise</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypotheses or data first?</title>
      <link>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2010 11:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first/</guid>
      <description>The recent nature issue had an interesting point-counterpoint series of 2 articles as a reflection on 10 years of the human genome project. The first article argues that hypotheses should come first because little progress has been made in the last 10 years as a result of the abundance of data from these different genome projects. The second article argues the exact opposite, that this data-driven approach has resulted in a series of break-troughs that could not have been possible with a hypothesis-driven approach.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>