<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Karl Cottenie on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>/tags/karl-cottenie/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Karl Cottenie on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 10:17:17 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/karl-cottenie/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Bring your kid to work day</title>
      <link>/post/kids_at_work/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 10:17:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/kids_at_work/</guid>
      <description>On November 5, it was bring your kid to work day for Grade 9 students. My oldest son (Kobe) wanted to participate, so I created a fun-packed (I thought) day for him.
The highlight for him: siting in on Sho and Nick&amp;rsquo;s Biodiversity class. At dinner that evening, he could tell us all about what he learned in that class.
The lowlight for him: my biostats class. Hopefully I have not ruined statistics for him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metacommunity Workshop in Belem</title>
      <link>/post/metacommunity_workshop_belem/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 10:17:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/metacommunity_workshop_belem/</guid>
      <description>I (Karl Cottenie) had a busy weeklong trip to Belem, Brazil, at the end of October. I was invited to facilitate a 2.5 day workshop, give a research seminar, and be part of an MSc qualifying defence.
See here for some pictures of my trip, and below is a little bit more information on what I did.
It was really fun (and a lot of work) to put together the material for the metacommunity workshop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google Scholar profile</title>
      <link>/post/google-scholar-profile/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2011 13:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/google-scholar-profile/</guid>
      <description>Nature has a news article on 2 free alternatives to Web of Science, including your personal citation library. Another example of serendipity, because I created one a couple of days before the nature publication, and planned to wanted to dedicate a short blog to it, i.e., this one.&amp;nbsp;
You can access mine here:&amp;nbsp;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=lL7RlhMAAAAJ. Below is a 2011 snapshot picture:For reference, here is screen capture of the &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; Web of Science summary:Very similar, if you ask me, although the Google Scholar obviously includes more items.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>