<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>conference on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>/tags/conference/</link>
    <description>Recent content in conference on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 19:56:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/conference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Making science matter</title>
      <link>/post/making-science-matter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 19:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/making-science-matter/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I found myself eavesdropping on two elderly fellows debating an age-old question: does size matter? Yes! declared one. Small ones have never satisfied anyone. It needs to be big!You’ve got it all wrong,countered the other. Proper use of a small one can be just as good as having a big one. And what good is a big one if you don’t use it properly?/o:pIn a nearby lecture theatre the Costa-Rican Mermaid was preaching the power of long distance swimming to promote big ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The world of conferences</title>
      <link>/post/the-world-of-conferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2010 16:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-world-of-conferences/</guid>
      <description>I also had the opportunity to attend a conference this week, the 5th annual meeting of the Canadian Society for Ecology and Evolution, held at the Universite Laval. It was a well organized conference with a lot of energy and some very interesting talks and posters. Quebec City served as a wonderful setting for the conference and I was impressed by how the conference was truly bilingual. I was also impressed by vieux Quebec and the beauty of the St.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out with rote learning</title>
      <link>/post/out-with-rote-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2010 10:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/out-with-rote-learning/</guid>
      <description>Tom Nudds and I co-taught community ecology for the first time together last semester (and Amanda was one of our wonderful TAs). Despite our differences ;-), we share a very similar teaching philosophy. And as a result of some crazy ideas, we decided to completely remodel community ecology. Tom&amp;rsquo;s rallying cry:
Out with rote learningTo implement this, we cut out all &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; aspects of grading in our course, and instead we implemented 3 research projects in a problem-based learning framework.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>