<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>fun on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/fun/</link>
    <description>Recent content in fun on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 09:02:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/fun/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientific communication: blogging and publishing?</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/scientific-communication-blogging-and-publishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 09:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/scientific-communication-blogging-and-publishing/</guid>
      <description>Fletcher Halliday,blogging at BioDiverse Perspectives, wrote:
&amp;ldquo;My original intent in writing this post was to compare the 5 most-cited papers on biodiversity to the 5 most blogged-about papers on biodiversity to address the differences between what we value as researchers versus what we value as general science communicators.&amp;rdquo;
What struck me throughout this post was this, maybe implicit, need to distinguish between blogging and publications. I always approach a publication as a communication of ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is ecology, and evolution - the value of interdisciplinary collaboration?</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/what-is-ecology-and-evolution-the-value-of-interdisciplinary-collaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 08:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/what-is-ecology-and-evolution-the-value-of-interdisciplinary-collaboration/</guid>
      <description>What is ecology? What is evolution? Seems like a really simple question from an ecology or evolution perspective, until you bring a different field into the mix, e.g., transposon/genome biology. When we started the TE (formerly known as genome) ecology group, sometimes in March 2010, I had no idea we would end here, with a publication in a journal with a higher impact factor than Ecology.
Our starting point for this publication was the appeal of using ecological theory to explore the dynamics of transposable elements in the genome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indiana Jones denied tenure</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/indiana-jones-denied-tenure/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2012 08:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/indiana-jones-denied-tenure/</guid>
      <description>http://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/back-from-yet-another-globetrotting-adventure-indiana-jones-checks-his-mail-and-discovers-that-his-bid-for-tenure-has-been-denied
&amp;ldquo;The lone student representative on the committee wished to convey that, besides being an exceptional instructor, a compassionate mentor, and an unparalleled gentleman, Dr. Jones was extraordinarily receptive to the female student body during and after the transition to a coeducational system at the college. However, his timeliness in grading and returning assignments was a concern.&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brittany defended yesterday...</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/brittany-defended-yesterday.../</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2012 10:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/brittany-defended-yesterday.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; successfully, of course. Now we just have to turn it into a publication. I always give a short speech during the celebrations afterwards, and the theme was what Brittany, her personality, brought to the research project (Ryan Gregory&amp;rsquo;s great standard question). She was much too modest when she answered this during her defence, so I answered it for her:
her organizational talents (keeping track of the extensive experiments and field observations, all at the same time)her efficient and hard work (she counted more than 600 samples one summer, compared to my 90+ samples for my entire PhD)her intellectual contributions to her thesis, which looks very straightforward afterward, but it took us many iterations to understand and explain it this clearlyknowing how to handle me (important one!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making fun of professors</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/making-fun-of-professors/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2012 13:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/making-fun-of-professors/</guid>
      <description>It is so easy to make fun of professors, we even have our own comic strip. If you believe the stereotype, we have so many laughable traits that there is a never ending list of possible punch lines. The sad part, some (most?) of them can hit really close to home.
Recently McSweeney&amp;rsquo;s published a more elaborate punch line on philosophy to answer:
&amp;ldquo;UNIVERSE&amp;rsquo;S FUNDAMENTAL QUESTION&amp;rdquo;&amp;nbsp;This is a golden oldie, and apparently it made the internet rounds already, but I became aware of it through Geekdad (what&amp;rsquo;s in a name, right?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>End of semester</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/end-of-semester/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2012 15:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/end-of-semester/</guid>
      <description>I am about to submit the grades for the two courses this semester, and this often leads to self reflection. I am not going to do that now, but I will do something better: link to the self reflection of a teacher that is well-written, funny, insightful, sometimes reflects my own experiences, sometimes not at all. So I highly recommend William Bowers&amp;rsquo; &amp;ldquo;All we read is freaks&amp;rdquo;&amp;nbsp;for all educators.
I could extract so many passages out of this long piece, but this is the one I emailed to myself:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R-hipster confession</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/r-hipster-confession/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2012 10:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/r-hipster-confession/</guid>
      <description>I sometimes think of myself as a science nerd, but then I read Benjamin Mako Hill&amp;rsquo;s computing set-up, and suddenly it&amp;rsquo;s like reading the uber science nerd manifesto. Amazingly consistent and hard-core, every single step of his work flow. And where our work flows overlap is probably in R:
&amp;nbsp;&amp;ldquo;R is slow and using it with big datasets gives one plenty of time to reflect on this fact. But R is also expressive, elegant, and concise for numerical and statistical work so I happily suffer through it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A call to all aquatic nerds...</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/a-call-to-all-aquatic-nerds.../</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2012 09:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/a-call-to-all-aquatic-nerds.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; how many species can you identify in this video?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talking to...</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/talking-to.../</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 16:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/talking-to.../</guid>
      <description>As you probably noticed, we do lots of interdisciplinary research in this lab. A group of undergraduate students approached this question for a 4th year class, and made a website that approaches interdisciplinary research from, you guessed it, several different perspectives. One of the activities they did was interviewing a wide range of people with this question in mind. Two of those persons where Ingrid and myself. And I will leave it up to you to find those,&amp;nbsp;embarrassing ?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Farewells</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/farewells/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2012 13:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/farewells/</guid>
      <description>There is a time of arriving, and a time of leaving, and the time of leaving has arrived. Thiago and his family is going back to Brazil, after a very successful, productive, and fun 6 month visit. Now I have to find a way to visit Brazil, somehow, sometime. The lab will be a little bit quieter, again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Cottenie commandments - illustrated</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-cottenie-commandments-illustrated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2012 14:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-cottenie-commandments-illustrated/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s been a long time since I focused on this, but I found some nice illustrations for some of them. The illustrations in this post by Maria Popova&amp;nbsp;reminded my of the 10 Commandments. I looked through the other posters on the original website Advice to Sink in Slowly, and actually found an illustration for every commandment:
1. reveal curiosity/passion
Andy J Miller2. tell a story
Mathew Isherwood
3. great dreamLee Basford</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sugarcoating the poisonous dagger</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/sugarcoating-the-poisonous-dagger/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2012 11:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/sugarcoating-the-poisonous-dagger/</guid>
      <description>Philosophers have a way with words. Since they work with the exploration of ideas, describing those ideas in words is essential. I have now collaborated with several philosophers, and I am continuously in awe of their mastery of language. It makes me question everything I write myself, what words I use, why I use them, definitions, meanings, &amp;hellip;
Here is another example in the ecological literature of an exchange between an scientist, Root Gorlick, and a philosopher, Mark Colyvan (and immediately I start thinking whether I should use &amp;ldquo;scientist&amp;rdquo;, because does this imply that a philosopher is not a scientist, should it be better to use biologist, but then Root Gorlick is also affiliated with Math&amp;amp;Stats, you see the rabbit hole you quickly fall into?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Musical stats</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/musical-stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2011 10:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/musical-stats/</guid>
      <description>Who thought stats would enter into every aspect of life? What about a Belgian dj duo called Mumbai Science, with the track &amp;ldquo;Ancova&amp;rdquo;?

And this thanks to 2 Many Dj&amp;rsquo;s and Music for Life 2011.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fun with stats</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/fun-with-stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2011 09:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/fun-with-stats/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes stats are sad funny (see this post), and sometimes both fun funny and timely. Seethe latest from PhD Comics:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to lie with politics (and statistics)</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/how-to-lie-with-politics-and-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2011 10:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/how-to-lie-with-politics-and-statistics/</guid>
      <description>Great analysis about the usage of figures in politics:&amp;nbsp;http://flowingdata.com/2011/12/12/fox-news-still-makes-awesome-charts/
What&amp;rsquo;s wrong with this figure?

See the original post for the answer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Doodling, or justifying my whiteboard</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/doodling-or-justifying-my-whiteboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2011 16:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/doodling-or-justifying-my-whiteboard/</guid>
      <description>One of the best spent $200.00 are not for a fraction of my laptop or desktop, or for my favourite books on R code, or for part of the cost to an exiting conference, but for my giant whiteboard in my office. I use it daily for doodling:
&amp;ldquo;To make spontaneous marks to help yourself think&amp;rdquo;

Another great TED talk, this time by Sunni Brown.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embryo - or the screen writing of the scientific method</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/embryo-or-the-screen-writing-of-the-scientific-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2011 14:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/embryo-or-the-screen-writing-of-the-scientific-method/</guid>
      <description>According to Christopher Booker, there are seven basic plots. I had always the intuition that the scientific method was an example of &amp;ldquo;the quest&amp;rdquo;: the scientist (i.e., hero) goes looking for something, often with collaborators. But I never thought that the link between story telling and the scientific method would be so obvious. I recently read an article in Wired about Dan Harmon, the creator of and screen writer for Community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So true</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/so-true/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2011 15:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/so-true/</guid>
      <description>I could link to all the new versions ofPHD Comics, but this one made me laugh so hard, I had to repost it:
I am guilty of this at least twice a day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complexity...</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/complexity.../</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 14:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/complexity.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; or ecology meet TED.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brittany&#39;s first publication!</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/brittanys-first-publication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2011 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/brittanys-first-publication/</guid>
      <description>Brittany&amp;rsquo;s first publication stemming from her undergraduate research project during the Algonquin field course has just been published. She was part of team IDH (for obvious reasons), and they worked their butts of to collect the data: finding an interesting question based on her previous community ecology course, interviewing park people to find stands with known time-to-logging, collecting the data, tiring out the TAs who helped them (or maybe slowed them down), breaking down her field vehicle, of course exactly on the one day I came out with them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Translating research</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/translating-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 13:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/translating-research/</guid>
      <description>Amanda is currently trying to publish the first chapter of her thesis (whohoo), and this can do funny things to your brain. See the post on her personal blog on how research findings are translated through the different media outlets, or the scientific version of telephone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Definition of teaching</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/definition-of-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2011 10:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/definition-of-teaching/</guid>
      <description>I could not resist posting this cartoon. It defines what teaching is: creating a process that moves a learner from the left-hand circle to the right-hand circle, nothing more, nothing less. Creating that process efficiently and effectively, however, is of course a completely different question.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical ecologists</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/theoretical-ecologists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2010 11:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/theoretical-ecologists/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever felt insecure, inferior, stupid, when talking to a theoretical ecologist? Here is your fall back position:
Physicists: &amp;ldquo;&amp;ldquo;
Just replace &amp;ldquo;physicist&amp;rdquo; with &amp;ldquo;theoretical ecologist&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;liberal-arts majors&amp;rdquo; with yourself, and you regain the upper hand again in any discussion ;-)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The power of graphics</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-power-of-graphics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2010 16:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-power-of-graphics/</guid>
      <description>Intelligent persons have written wonderful books about creating good graphs. Today, I received two graphs in my Google Reader, and they make such powerful/funny statements that I had to show them, especially since they are visually so comparable.
In the funny category:

In the powerful category (click here for the original article with more powerful visuals):

It&amp;rsquo;s very unlikely that anything in my research career will produce anything that funny, or could influence the voting behaviour of a whole nation, but we can only try.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confessions of a grad student</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/confessions-of-a-grad-student/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2010 11:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/confessions-of-a-grad-student/</guid>
      <description>Are you intrigued by these snippets?I like statsI dislike learning R&amp;nbsp;results may be meaninglessTedious? Yes. Accurate? Yes&amp;nbsp;Then go over to&amp;nbsp;Amanda&#39;s latest blog post.&amp;nbsp; </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BBQ potluck</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/bbq-potluck/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2010 12:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/bbq-potluck/</guid>
      <description>It is that time of the year again, the evenings are getting shorter and colder, the get-back-to-school ads are &amp;nbsp;being replaced with Halloween ads, Guelph seems to girding itself for the onslaught of 17.000 partying students with campaigns, more police patrols, warnings, new by-laws, field work is winding down and everybody is slowly adjusting to the realities of life. To celebrate this past summer, and introduce all the new lab members to each other, we had our first unofficial lab meeting at my place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientists measure...</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/scientists-measure.../</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2010 15:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/scientists-measure.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; all kinds of things. See Amanda&amp;rsquo;s latest post from Churchill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bike Lessons</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/bike-lessons/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 19:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/bike-lessons/</guid>
      <description>I am Ingrid, a returning member of the Cottenie lab. This is my first post, and it comes at one of those in-between times in my life. I am in between finishing a two-month bike tour and starting a three- (or four, or more&amp;hellip;?) year PhD. It&amp;rsquo;s been an interesting process, returning from the tour and re-integrating back into society.
First, a little about the tour. It was one of the best and most challenging things I have ever done.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Field work is winding down in Churchill</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/field-work-is-winding-down-in-churchill/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2010 15:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/field-work-is-winding-down-in-churchill/</guid>
      <description>Mid august, and it is starting to feel like summer is indeed slowly winding down.
Amanda is also feeling signs ofFall in Churchill, and Brittany has just put an update about her first field season up there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sub-arctic outreach</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/sub-arctic-outreach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jun 2010 13:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/sub-arctic-outreach/</guid>
      <description>Is it possible that grade 3 kids are more interested in zooplankton than 3year university students? Click here to find out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amanda&#39;s first blog post of the season</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/amandas-first-blog-post-of-the-season/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2010 13:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/amandas-first-blog-post-of-the-season/</guid>
      <description>about trains, plains, and canoes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some pre fieldwork fieldwork</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/some-pre-fieldwork-fieldwork/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 22:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/some-pre-fieldwork-fieldwork/</guid>
      <description>Today Brittany and I took a walk over to the Arboretum to sample some of the temporary and man-made ponds, as part of an ongoing metacommunity study. With the warm spring we&amp;rsquo;ve been having, the zooplankton are in full swing, rivalling the communities we found in Churchill last year in August!Here Brittany is marvelling at the zooplankton and many aquatic insects:

Notice the tea-coloured water, it is stained by tannins leaching from the fallen leaves and detritus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More costumes</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/more-costumes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2010 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/more-costumes/</guid>
      <description>How many do you need to make a costume? Apparently more than 5. However, based on this last evening, we now have a full design, including the know-how on how to make it. So the next time we meet, we should have 6 full Daphnia costumes for the parade.&amp;nbsp;4 degrees to work with papier mache, your quality education at work
To illustrate that this is part of the rostrum, all you dirty minds&amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let the costumes begin!</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/let-the-costumes-begin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Mar 2010 10:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/let-the-costumes-begin/</guid>
      <description>Well, as Karl has mentioned our lab will be participating as a horde of zooplankton in the KW Procession of Species Parade. The parade is as much about encouragaing local expressions of art as it is about showcasing biodiversity. With that in mind we set out yesterday to stretch our creativity and construct a prototype of our first costume. We decided that Daphnia would be our main inspiration and started on a carapace and post abdomen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The planktoneers make headlines!</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-planktoneers-make-headlines/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2010 11:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-planktoneers-make-headlines/</guid>
      <description>We will participate as a lab to the species parade in Kitchener/Waterloo. Our theme? The planktoneers, of course. This seems not to be the most obvious theme, so we are mentioned in some of the local papers. As Ingrid wrote: &amp;ldquo;The heat is on&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>