<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>science on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>/tags/science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in science on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 08:34:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What is ecology, and evolution - the value of interdisciplinary collaboration?</title>
      <link>/post/what-is-ecology-and-evolution-the-value-of-interdisciplinary-collaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 08:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/what-is-ecology-and-evolution-the-value-of-interdisciplinary-collaboration/</guid>
      <description>What is ecology? What is evolution? Seems like a really simple question from an ecology or evolution perspective, until you bring a different field into the mix, e.g., transposon/genome biology. When we started the TE (formerly known as genome) ecology group, sometimes in March 2010, I had no idea we would end here, with a publication in a journal with a higher impact factor than Ecology.
Our starting point for this publication was the appeal of using ecological theory to explore the dynamics of transposable elements in the genome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The role of intuition in data analysis</title>
      <link>/post/the-role-of-intuition-in-data-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2012 07:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-role-of-intuition-in-data-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Most of you readers probably followed the US elections with varying degrees of interest and passion, but as scientists are also aware of the &amp;ldquo;role&amp;rdquo; of Nate Silver and his blog FiveThirtyEight.com. Lots has been written about his success, which is &amp;ldquo;just&amp;rdquo; a nice example of the strengths of the scientific process, and thus not that surprising. What does&amp;nbsp;surprise&amp;nbsp;me, is the reluctance of journalists to come to terms with what he does.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metacommunity terminology</title>
      <link>/post/metacommunity-terminology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Apr 2012 09:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/metacommunity-terminology/</guid>
      <description>The title of my &amp;ldquo;Teaching Philosophy&amp;rdquo; statement (that I completely rewrite every year), is &amp;ldquo;Research-Teaching-Learning Link&amp;rdquo;. In it, I try to point out the obvious and maybe not so obvious connections between these different aspects of my professional life. One of the items that is hardest to prove, though, is how teaching can inform my day-to-day research focus.
And now I can finally provide evidence for this: our comment in Trends in Ecology and Evolution &amp;ldquo;The terminology of metacommunity ecology&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The fallacy of our misunderstand of the scientific method</title>
      <link>/post/the-fallacy-of-our-misunderstand-of-the-scientific-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2012 11:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-fallacy-of-our-misunderstand-of-the-scientific-method/</guid>
      <description>Ryan Norris via Tom Nudds sent me a link to this web site, and I think all three of us had the same &amp;ldquo;What the &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; reaction after reading the entry by Irene Pepperberg, titled &amp;ldquo;The Fallacy of Hypothesis Testing&amp;rdquo;:
&amp;ldquo;I was trained, as a chemist, to use the classic scientific method: Devise a testable hypothesis, and then design an experiment to see if the hypothesis is correct or not. And I was told that this method is equally valid for the social sciences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientific debate...</title>
      <link>/post/scientific-debate.../</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2012 12:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/scientific-debate.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; rests on actually reading and understanding each other&amp;rsquo;s words.
This is a difficult exercise, and not only for students. Tom Nudds and I just covered in community ecology the rationale for protected areas planning based not only on representativeness (making sure that all species are protected), but more importantly also on persistence (see his article in Biodiversity and Conservation for a summary of their ideas). If the target areas have all the species you want to conserve, but lack essential components that would ensure their actual persistence through time, representativeness means nothing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Context is everything</title>
      <link>/post/context-is-everything/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 10:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/context-is-everything/</guid>
      <description>An interesting paper in Science by Stumpf and Porter&amp;nbsp;takes a hard look at &amp;ldquo;general&amp;rdquo; power laws in science:
&amp;ldquo;A striking feature that has attracted considerable attention is the apparent ubiquity of power-law relationships in empirical data. However, although power laws have been reported in areas ranging from finance and molecular biology to geophysics and the Internet, the data are typically insufficient and the mechanistic insights are almost always too limited for the identification of power-law behavior to be scientifically useful (see the figure).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science and uncertainty</title>
      <link>/post/science-and-uncertainty/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2012 14:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/science-and-uncertainty/</guid>
      <description>I just started teaching Community Ecology with Tom Nudds again, and one of the main themes of this course is exposing students to the importance of uncertainty in science (or Science, if you want). Today anotherinsightful article by John Timmer in Ars Technica appeared, and provides a real-life example of this&amp;nbsp;uncertainty.
It tells the story of Peter Duesburg, a scientist with an impressive academic history:
&amp;ldquo;He did pioneering work in the characterization of retroviruses (viruses that are transmitted using RNA as a genetic material, but then copied into DNA and inserted into their hosts&amp;rsquo; genome), helping to show that they could pick up genes from their host that enabled them to induce cancer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The importance of constraints</title>
      <link>/post/the-importance-of-constraints/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 16:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-importance-of-constraints/</guid>
      <description>For me, one of the biggest mysteries of the scientific method (see e.g. this post), is that it provides such a rigid structure, yet at the same time so creative. It turns out that constraints actually lead to more global, conceptual, and maybe thus more creative thinking.Jonah Lehrer in Wired provides some excellent context for a recent study that investigated this link explicitly. Highly recommended.
At the same time, this could also explain one of my other pet peeves: why concept mapping is such a powerful method.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embryo - or the screen writing of the scientific method</title>
      <link>/post/embryo-or-the-screen-writing-of-the-scientific-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2011 14:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/embryo-or-the-screen-writing-of-the-scientific-method/</guid>
      <description>According to Christopher Booker, there are seven basic plots. I had always the intuition that the scientific method was an example of &amp;ldquo;the quest&amp;rdquo;: the scientist (i.e., hero) goes looking for something, often with collaborators. But I never thought that the link between story telling and the scientific method would be so obvious. I recently read an article in Wired about Dan Harmon, the creator of and screen writer for Community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Datateller</title>
      <link>/post/datateller/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 10:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/datateller/</guid>
      <description>As I recently noticed, the majority of my posts here are unconsciously driven by the courses that I am preparing. The couple of posts on natural history and science are basically an illustration to my field course that I will be teaching next week (hopefully I will get some time to blog from the field). And in the fall, I will be teaching a grad stats course for the first time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google Scholar profile</title>
      <link>/post/google-scholar-profile/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2011 13:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/google-scholar-profile/</guid>
      <description>Nature has a news article on 2 free alternatives to Web of Science, including your personal citation library. Another example of serendipity, because I created one a couple of days before the nature publication, and planned to wanted to dedicate a short blog to it, i.e., this one.&amp;nbsp;
You can access mine here:&amp;nbsp;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=lL7RlhMAAAAJ. Below is a 2011 snapshot picture:For reference, here is screen capture of the &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; Web of Science summary:Very similar, if you ask me, although the Google Scholar obviously includes more items.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation</title>
      <link>/post/presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2011 11:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/presentation/</guid>
      <description>Since I started reading a lot of long-form articles on the internet, I have been exposed to a lot of great ideas, and great writing. The latest is an article by Steven Shapin in the London Review of Books, The Darwin Show. He synthesized 14 (fourteen!) books that appeared around the celebration of his 200th birthday in 2009. In it, he explores a lot of interesting themes, and one of the main ones revolves around why this is such a big deal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Athena, the nerd god.</title>
      <link>/post/athena-the-nerd-god./</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2011 10:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/athena-the-nerd-god./</guid>
      <description>Robin Sloan wrote abeautiful short story (The truth about the east wind), with a very interesting format. It looks at the tension between religion and science, from a Greek tragedy perspective (you should really read it).
&amp;ldquo;Zeus formed it into a girl and set her free to walk the earth. This was Athena. Pure curiosity. The spark made flesh.&amp;nbsp;From the day she was formed, Athena was an omnivorous observer, a kind of super Galileo/Darwin long before either was born.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative vs. qualitative?</title>
      <link>/post/quantitative-vs.-qualitative/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2011 11:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/quantitative-vs.-qualitative/</guid>
      <description>Ingrid and I had a discussion the other day about whether quantitative or qualitative data make a more lasting impression. As you might have guessed, I am more on the quantitative side, and Ingrid more on the qualitative side ;-) And me being me, I created a visual scenario about a result from Ingrid&amp;rsquo;s thesis (the importance of deep community in successful conservation) that was applied in 100 new conservation efforts (or replicate experiments, without controls, though).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Picture blog 2</title>
      <link>/post/picture-blog-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 11:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/picture-blog-2/</guid>
      <description>My old lab space.

New lab space. Much more organized.

H.arcticus for my first LC50.

The box I constructed to control the light for my LC50.

Inside the box.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common versus rare species in a metacommunity context</title>
      <link>/post/common-versus-rare-species-in-a-metacommunity-context/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2011 11:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/common-versus-rare-species-in-a-metacommunity-context/</guid>
      <description>It is finally online, the first publication from the Brazilian side of the lab ;-). In this article, we made competing predictions about how common and rare species should behave in a metacommunity context. The, very surprising, result was that both common and rare species reacted very similarly to environmental gradients, which was very counterintuitive from both a metacommunity and macro-ecology point of view.

Another side effect of this study was our new definition for rareness, based on a slightly subjective but less arbitrary definition compared to other studies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making science matter</title>
      <link>/post/making-science-matter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 19:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/making-science-matter/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I found myself eavesdropping on two elderly fellows debating an age-old question: does size matter? Yes! declared one. Small ones have never satisfied anyone. It needs to be big!You’ve got it all wrong,countered the other. Proper use of a small one can be just as good as having a big one. And what good is a big one if you don’t use it properly?/o:pIn a nearby lecture theatre the Costa-Rican Mermaid was preaching the power of long distance swimming to promote big ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Link between improvement of the environment and society?</title>
      <link>/post/link-between-improvement-of-the-environment-and-society/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 11:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/link-between-improvement-of-the-environment-and-society/</guid>
      <description>While I am aware of my tendency to discount anything older as 10 years as ancient in science terms, I do try to sketch a brief historical of each issue I discuss in (most of) my research articles. However, I am always surprised by the lack of &amp;ldquo;history&amp;rdquo; in quality reporting on scientific progress.&amp;nbsp;A recent story in Nature, &amp;ldquo;Can conservation cut poverty&amp;rdquo;, investigated the link between preserving biodiversity and positive influences this might have on the local inhabitants.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Natural history = basis of interest</title>
      <link>/post/natural-history-basis-of-interest/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2011 13:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/natural-history-basis-of-interest/</guid>
      <description>Last year, I wrote a couple of posts about the importance of natural history in science:
http://www.cottenielab.org/2010/04/hypotheses-or-data-first.htmlhttp://www.cottenielab.org/2010/04/hypotheses-or-data-first-update.htmlhttp://www.cottenielab.org/2010/04/hypotheses-or-data-first-update-2.htmlI argued that natural history forms the basis of the scientific method, but I also acknowledged that the power of the scientific method came from the interaction between data and hypotheses, yadayada.&amp;nbsp;
However, one important thing that I forgot to add in that discussion is that natural history does not only form the basis of the scientific method, but also the basis of our interest in science.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The scientific method and our health</title>
      <link>/post/the-scientific-method-and-our-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 15:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-scientific-method-and-our-health/</guid>
      <description>There are several ways to define &amp;ldquo;science&amp;rdquo;, but here is very basic one byEdzard Ernst, the first professor in &amp;nbsp;Alternative Medicine, in an interview in Science:
&amp;ldquo;I was also convinced that scientists need to be critical and sceptical, and that if you apply science to any field you don&amp;rsquo;t want to prove that your ideas are correct, you want to test whether they are correct.&amp;rdquo;While I probably have to check his own summary of his scientific legacy (&amp;rdquo;I found that homeopathy is pretty useless.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complexity...</title>
      <link>/post/complexity.../</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 14:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/complexity.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; or ecology meet TED.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy day - sad day, part II</title>
      <link>/post/happy-day-sad-day-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 11:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/happy-day-sad-day-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>The end of the semester is always hectic. Especially this year, since our lab had three year-long undergrad thesis students working away on various projects.
Brittany Ferguson worked this semester on whether duck dispersal influenced macroinvertebrate metacommunity patterns. She found one of those very zen-like conclusions, where the absence of a predicted pattern is actually evidence for the importance of the process, and we will expose her zen-conclusions hopefully sometime this summer to the very critical research community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brittany&#39;s first publication!</title>
      <link>/post/brittanys-first-publication/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2011 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/brittanys-first-publication/</guid>
      <description>Brittany&amp;rsquo;s first publication stemming from her undergraduate research project during the Algonquin field course has just been published. She was part of team IDH (for obvious reasons), and they worked their butts of to collect the data: finding an interesting question based on her previous community ecology course, interviewing park people to find stands with known time-to-logging, collecting the data, tiring out the TAs who helped them (or maybe slowed them down), breaking down her field vehicle, of course exactly on the one day I came out with them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy day - sad day, part 1</title>
      <link>/post/happy-day-sad-day-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2011 09:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/happy-day-sad-day-part-1/</guid>
      <description>All good things come to an end. And now it is Amanda&#39;s time to leave. She successfully defended her thesis &#34;Zooplankton metacommunity responses to environmental change in the sub-arctic&#34;. At this point, there are 3 manifestations of her work:Amanda&#39;s electronic thesis link: the UoG library now provides an electronic reference for all theses, which will increase the exposure and accessibility of the research.Her presentation, that is the perfect example of how we should present results to a larger audience</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Translating research</title>
      <link>/post/translating-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 13:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/translating-research/</guid>
      <description>Amanda is currently trying to publish the first chapter of her thesis (whohoo), and this can do funny things to your brain. See the post on her personal blog on how research findings are translated through the different media outlets, or the scientific version of telephone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metacommunity dynamics in the prairie pothole region</title>
      <link>/post/metacommunity-dynamics-in-the-prairie-pothole-region/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2011 19:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/metacommunity-dynamics-in-the-prairie-pothole-region/</guid>
      <description>The prairie pothole region, characterized by millions of unique ponds scattered across its surface extends from Alberta Canada, down into the central United States. This “patchy” ecosystem provides feeding habitat for an estimated 50-75% of North Americas breeding ducks, which feed primarily on the numerable invertebrate species found within the area.  The region is an ideal site for the study of metacommunity dynamics, as it’s many local ecosystems (ponds) are joined by the dispersal of highly interactive species (ducks and invertebrates).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another inspirational video</title>
      <link>/post/another-inspirational-video/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2010 11:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/another-inspirational-video/</guid>
      <description>This video touches all my buttons: teaching, education, collaboration, comics, story telling, science, humor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Empty Cups</title>
      <link>/post/empty-cups/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2010 14:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/empty-cups/</guid>
      <description>Very occasionally, I will brave North American culture and go see a movie on a ridiculously big screen with a ridiculously big bag of popcorn. Last December, a friend convinced me to not only go see Avatar on the big screen, but to watch it in 3-D with her. I was blown away. Though I find the current 3-D craze to be, well, crazy, I have to admit that it brought a certain enchantment to the fantasy planet Pandora.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What can science learn from Google?</title>
      <link>/post/what-can-science-learn-from-google/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2010 14:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/what-can-science-learn-from-google/</guid>
      <description>That is the finishing sentence from&amp;nbsp;this article. The author tries to argue that theory and the scientific method is getting obsolete in this day and age, using Google as a role model:
But faced with massive data, this approach to science — hypothesize, model, test — is becoming obsolete. [&amp;hellip;] There is now a better way. Petabytes allow us to say: &amp;ldquo;Correlation is enough.&amp;rdquo; We can stop looking for models. We can analyze the data without hypotheses about what it might show.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecofeminism: not just tree-hugging and hairy legs</title>
      <link>/post/ecofeminism-not-just-tree-hugging-and-hairy-legs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2010 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/ecofeminism-not-just-tree-hugging-and-hairy-legs/</guid>
      <description>In March 2009, the Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies undergraduate program (among others) was cut at Guelph. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t involved in the issue myself, but knew a few people who rallied against this decision. They cited it as ironic evidence that feminism is far from being a finished movement. At the time, I only saw a superficial link between the Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies program cut and feminism; I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what feminism really was.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A remedy for inaccessible science?</title>
      <link>/post/a-remedy-for-inaccessible-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2010 09:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/a-remedy-for-inaccessible-science/</guid>
      <description>One of the most common complaints about the world of science is it&amp;rsquo;s inaccessibility to the everyday person. Carl Zimmer has put together an &amp;ldquo;Index of Banned Words&amp;rdquo;. Words that should be vanquished from the vocabulary of scientists everywhere. The list includes the taboos &amp;ldquo;elucidate&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;predation&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;mechanism&amp;rdquo;, and (gasp!) &amp;ldquo;community ecology&amp;rdquo;.
Reading through the list has made me realize how incredibly predictable my choice of words has become when writing in my science courses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical ecologists</title>
      <link>/post/theoretical-ecologists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2010 11:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/theoretical-ecologists/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever felt insecure, inferior, stupid, when talking to a theoretical ecologist? Here is your fall back position:
Physicists: &amp;ldquo;&amp;ldquo;
Just replace &amp;ldquo;physicist&amp;rdquo; with &amp;ldquo;theoretical ecologist&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;liberal-arts majors&amp;rdquo; with yourself, and you regain the upper hand again in any discussion ;-)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scaling up</title>
      <link>/post/scaling-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2010 16:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/scaling-up/</guid>
      <description>In our lab, we focus mainly on metacommunity dynamics, or how the interactions between dispersal and local environmental processes influence communities in the landscape. Since we are interested in communities in the landscape, we automatically deal with the issue of &amp;ldquo;scale&amp;rdquo;. This is one of those very diffuse concepts in ecology, with as many definitions as scientists (temporal, spatial, conceptual, grain, &amp;hellip;).
This&amp;nbsp;recent article by Spivak et al. in Freshwater Biology&amp;nbsp;tackles a problem experimentally that is not often studied in ecology: how applicable are the results of small-scale experiments for empirical (and by default large-scale) systems?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The power of graphics</title>
      <link>/post/the-power-of-graphics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2010 16:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-power-of-graphics/</guid>
      <description>Intelligent persons have written wonderful books about creating good graphs. Today, I received two graphs in my Google Reader, and they make such powerful/funny statements that I had to show them, especially since they are visually so comparable.
In the funny category:

In the powerful category (click here for the original article with more powerful visuals):

It&amp;rsquo;s very unlikely that anything in my research career will produce anything that funny, or could influence the voting behaviour of a whole nation, but we can only try.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confessions of a grad student</title>
      <link>/post/confessions-of-a-grad-student/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2010 11:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/confessions-of-a-grad-student/</guid>
      <description>Are you intrigued by these snippets?I like statsI dislike learning R&amp;nbsp;results may be meaninglessTedious? Yes. Accurate? Yes&amp;nbsp;Then go over to&amp;nbsp;Amanda&#39;s latest blog post.&amp;nbsp; </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More science outreach in Churchill</title>
      <link>/post/more-science-outreach-in-churchill/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 13:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/more-science-outreach-in-churchill/</guid>
      <description>see here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Critical thinking: different perspectives</title>
      <link>/post/critical-thinking-different-perspectives/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jul 2010 12:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/critical-thinking-different-perspectives/</guid>
      <description>When we were preparing the grading rubric to assess critical thinking (which is more complicated than you might think), Marianne Staempfli found this very useful resource: The Critical Thinking Community.&amp;nbsp;While the website itself is&amp;nbsp;quaintly old-fashioned, it has a lot of useful information. For instance, a definition:
Critical thinking is the intellectually disciplined process of actively and skillfully conceptualizing, applying, analyzing, synthesizing, and/or evaluating information gathered from, or generated by, observation, experience, reflection, reasoning, or communication, as a guide to belief and action.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A metacommuntiy or a self-organized system?</title>
      <link>/post/a-metacommuntiy-or-a-self-organized-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2010 10:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/a-metacommuntiy-or-a-self-organized-system/</guid>
      <description>It is always interesting to read how scientists read, understand, and interpret articles in very different way. You can encounter this most often for your own results when you&amp;nbsp;present at a conference or seminar, and you get questions that throw you in a hoop, and&amp;nbsp;track the articles that refer to one of your publications (admit it, you do it too): often the first response is &#34;how could they interpret my text/data/interpretation in that context?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The scientific method: from intuition to data and back</title>
      <link>/post/the-scientific-method-from-intuition-to-data-and-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2010 12:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-scientific-method-from-intuition-to-data-and-back/</guid>
      <description>This is an article in the Globe and Mail that struck a cord with me,&amp;nbsp;&#34;Ten years that shook, rattled, rolled and helped repair the world&#34;&amp;nbsp;by Doug Saunders. If you do not have the time to read the full article, you can click on this shortened version with most of the salient points summarized in a concept map structure (make sure to click on it to see the bigger version so that you can actually read the text ;-):This article provides a very nice example of the&amp;nbsp;10th Cottenie Commandment: Thou Shalt Listen to thy Intuition, but Follow the Data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Concept maps: THE tool for learners?</title>
      <link>/post/concept-maps-the-tool-for-learners/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 11:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/concept-maps-the-tool-for-learners/</guid>
      <description>Learning (be it as a scientist, a teacher, a student, or any combination of the above, this will be the topic of another blog) is a difficult process, as any scientist, teacher, or student will tell you. However, sometimes you get struck by lightening, by an experience that makes you wonder, &amp;ldquo;How did I ever function without this?&amp;rdquo;. 3 years ago, I was introduced to concept mapping by Steve Crawford, but I am not exactly sure how we got on this subject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amanda&#39;s hatching experiment</title>
      <link>/post/amandas-hatching-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2010 09:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/amandas-hatching-experiment/</guid>
      <description>Ecology in action, life, in Churchill, with pictures, and explanations, using the magic of tupperware. Who said science is boring and expensive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lions and Tigers and ... Eelgrass??</title>
      <link>/post/lions-and-tigers-and-...-eelgrass/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2010 01:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/lions-and-tigers-and-...-eelgrass/</guid>
      <description>Oh hello there, community ecology enthusiasts I believe an introduction is in order. My name is Kyle and I am a recent addition to the Cottenie Lab. I will be undertaking an undergraduate research project under the guidance of Karl and the rest of the gang at CottenieLab beginning this fall (you may have seen my mug in a recent post on this blog in daphnia/stormtrooper attire!). First, a little bit about me&amp;hellip; my passions include diving, the outdoors and marine science (not necessarily in that order) and I have been fascinated with aquatic systems since spending my childhood summers sifting through tide pools on Canada’s east coast.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The world of conferences</title>
      <link>/post/the-world-of-conferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2010 16:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-world-of-conferences/</guid>
      <description>I also had the opportunity to attend a conference this week, the 5th annual meeting of the Canadian Society for Ecology and Evolution, held at the Universite Laval. It was a well organized conference with a lot of energy and some very interesting talks and posters. Quebec City served as a wonderful setting for the conference and I was impressed by how the conference was truly bilingual. I was also impressed by vieux Quebec and the beauty of the St.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some pre fieldwork fieldwork</title>
      <link>/post/some-pre-fieldwork-fieldwork/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 22:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/some-pre-fieldwork-fieldwork/</guid>
      <description>Today Brittany and I took a walk over to the Arboretum to sample some of the temporary and man-made ponds, as part of an ongoing metacommunity study. With the warm spring we&amp;rsquo;ve been having, the zooplankton are in full swing, rivalling the communities we found in Churchill last year in August!Here Brittany is marvelling at the zooplankton and many aquatic insects:

Notice the tea-coloured water, it is stained by tannins leaching from the fallen leaves and detritus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Field trip Carolinian forests</title>
      <link>/post/field-trip-carolinian-forests/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2010 18:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/field-trip-carolinian-forests/</guid>
      <description>In September, Marina will join our lab. She will study spatial patterns and metacommunity dynamics in Carolinian forest understory plants, and Andrew MacDougall is her co-advisor (since obviously I know nothing about plants). Today we visited 2 forest fragments, just to get an idea on the spatial (and temporal) scales of heterogeneity, and to get an idea of the practical considerations that drive the development of a research program.
The first set of pictures are some overviews of the different landscapes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embracing the digital article</title>
      <link>/post/embracing-the-digital-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2010 10:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/embracing-the-digital-article/</guid>
      <description>This is one of the best texts I have seen on the whole tablet reading experience, &amp;ldquo;Embracing the digital book&amp;rdquo; by Craig Mod. Not only very informative and well-argued, but also beautifully designed, which is of course the whole point of his article/journal.
But why do I mention this in this lab blog? Just imagine the possibilities if there would be a similar platform for scientific articles, that implements his ideas on &amp;ldquo;the network (or, e-reader &amp;lsquo;social&amp;rsquo; features)&amp;rdquo;:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The latest Birdfish</title>
      <link>/post/the-latest-birdfish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2010 18:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-latest-birdfish/</guid>
      <description>The Churchill Northern Studies Centre has hosted researchers from the Cottenie lab for the past couple years. This year we were invited to contribute a short write-up on our summer 2009 field season. You can read the article here:
http://www.churchillscience.ca/documents/Newsletter_Winter_2010.pdf
Also, be sure to check out the CNSC&amp;rsquo;s website for a preview of their new facility! The staff and volunteers at the CNSC are very supportive and a terrific resource for anyone doing science in the north.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypotheses or data first? Update 2</title>
      <link>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first-update-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 15:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first-update-2/</guid>
      <description>Since we seem to be on a roll on the what should come first in science, this Nature article actually presents a much better written and argued case in favour of combining the strengths of both approaches (maybe scientists should do what they are good at, science, and leave the writing to, journalists with a PhD?). Some of the costs for doing these genome studies: US$1 billion. How does that stack up to other funding, I have no idea, but this is a big number.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This is why we do this ...</title>
      <link>/post/this-is-why-we-do-this-.../</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2010 13:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/this-is-why-we-do-this-.../</guid>
      <description>research or science or playing or fun or exploration or whatever you want to call it.

Some background: Amanda, Ingrid, and Erin performed a very novel experiment in Churchill last summer (see their blog for more fun stuff). Amanda processed all the samples and is in the process of analyzing the data. Because of the design, it gets complicated very quickly, and so Amanda is honing her R-skills to visualize the results before we go p-value hunting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypotheses or data first - Update</title>
      <link>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2010 12:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first-update/</guid>
      <description>We discussed these two articles mentioned in a previous post in our Community Ecology class, and this is the summary of the very interesting discussion between the students, the TAs, and Tom and I:
It is not one or the other (which is actually acknowledges by using the &amp;ldquo;first&amp;rdquo; in the title)The scientific method is cyclical and depends on data, hypotheses, predictions, increased information, or is cyclical as is illustrated by TomBut I added (which was not supported by the majority of the students, or Tom ;-) that the start of the scientific method is data, or the description of a natural phenomenonI also tried to argue that the &amp;ldquo;hypotheses first&amp;rdquo; in its extreme is related to religion, since religion is essentially a hypothesis (causal mechanism) without data to support it, but at this point I was way outside my zone of expertise</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypotheses or data first?</title>
      <link>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2010 11:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hypotheses-or-data-first/</guid>
      <description>The recent nature issue had an interesting point-counterpoint series of 2 articles as a reflection on 10 years of the human genome project. The first article argues that hypotheses should come first because little progress has been made in the last 10 years as a result of the abundance of data from these different genome projects. The second article argues the exact opposite, that this data-driven approach has resulted in a series of break-troughs that could not have been possible with a hypothesis-driven approach.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>