<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>philosophy on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in philosophy on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 08:34:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What is ecology, and evolution - the value of interdisciplinary collaboration?</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/what-is-ecology-and-evolution-the-value-of-interdisciplinary-collaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 08:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/what-is-ecology-and-evolution-the-value-of-interdisciplinary-collaboration/</guid>
      <description>What is ecology? What is evolution? Seems like a really simple question from an ecology or evolution perspective, until you bring a different field into the mix, e.g., transposon/genome biology. When we started the TE (formerly known as genome) ecology group, sometimes in March 2010, I had no idea we would end here, with a publication in a journal with a higher impact factor than Ecology.
Our starting point for this publication was the appeal of using ecological theory to explore the dynamics of transposable elements in the genome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The role of intuition in data analysis</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-role-of-intuition-in-data-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2012 07:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-role-of-intuition-in-data-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Most of you readers probably followed the US elections with varying degrees of interest and passion, but as scientists are also aware of the &amp;ldquo;role&amp;rdquo; of Nate Silver and his blog FiveThirtyEight.com. Lots has been written about his success, which is &amp;ldquo;just&amp;rdquo; a nice example of the strengths of the scientific process, and thus not that surprising. What does&amp;nbsp;surprise&amp;nbsp;me, is the reluctance of journalists to come to terms with what he does.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sugarcoating the poisonous dagger</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/sugarcoating-the-poisonous-dagger/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2012 11:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/sugarcoating-the-poisonous-dagger/</guid>
      <description>Philosophers have a way with words. Since they work with the exploration of ideas, describing those ideas in words is essential. I have now collaborated with several philosophers, and I am continuously in awe of their mastery of language. It makes me question everything I write myself, what words I use, why I use them, definitions, meanings, &amp;hellip;
Here is another example in the ecological literature of an exchange between an scientist, Root Gorlick, and a philosopher, Mark Colyvan (and immediately I start thinking whether I should use &amp;ldquo;scientist&amp;rdquo;, because does this imply that a philosopher is not a scientist, should it be better to use biologist, but then Root Gorlick is also affiliated with Math&amp;amp;Stats, you see the rabbit hole you quickly fall into?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>