<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>grad school on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/grad-school/</link>
    <description>Recent content in grad school on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 May 2018 14:07:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/grad-school/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The benefits of academic workshops!</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-benefits-of-academic-workshops/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 May 2018 14:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-benefits-of-academic-workshops/</guid>
      <description>All IB graduate students should have received an email announcing the new batch of programs offered by the university to help graduate students with one of the most difficult academic skills: writing.
&amp;ldquo;Dear Graduate Faculty, Coordinators, and Graduate students, Our analytics indicate that those students who receive writing instruction and consultation early in their graduate programs complete their degree requirements sooner. Our programs are designed for graduate student writers at all levels and stages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Career preparation for graduate students.</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/career-preparation-for-graduate-students./</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 14:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/career-preparation-for-graduate-students./</guid>
      <description>This is an important issue, and I have already spent 4 news items on this. A recent publication in PLOS ONE investigated some of the strategies and resources PhD students (and postdocs) use for non-academic jobs. This is very important because more than 80% of our graduate students end in these non-academic jobs (although these numbers also includes MSc students). I should not have been surprised, but there are sociological theories and active research programs around this issue, resulting in publications where I am only comfortable reading the abstract and discussion, and hoping that the reviewers did their job.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science and passion</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/science-and-passion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2017 16:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/science-and-passion/</guid>
      <description>Since starting these news items, we have discussed themes related to mental health issues, their causes, and some solutions. Ardon Schnorr, a Biology PhD student at Carnegie Mellon University wrote a very powerful article around this theme that touches on a lot of issues surrounding this problem: http://www.chronicle.com/article/Grad-School-Is-Hard-on-Mental/240626. It is a must read for any graduate student. And if you are inspired by the positive effects of science communication, but do not know where to start, you can always start with the University of Guelph Let&amp;rsquo;s Talk Science outreach program.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blaming the victim, follow-up.</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/blaming-the-victim-follow-up./</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2017 11:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/blaming-the-victim-follow-up./</guid>
      <description>As expected, I was not the only one providing some push back to the Nature Jobs article&amp;nbsp;I discussed previously. Together, they make reasonable suggestions, both towards the supervisor, and the university. The&amp;nbsp;first one by D. A. McDonald&amp;nbsp;acknowledges that supervisors should be open aware of all aspects of their graduate students&amp;rsquo; lives (&amp;ldquo;what they do when they are not in the lab&amp;rdquo;). The&amp;nbsp;second one by D. Mehta and K. Vavitsas&amp;nbsp;point out institutional resources that can help tackle one of the root problems (&amp;ldquo;providing more courses and resources to train principal investigators in management and leadership&amp;rdquo;).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blaming the victim?</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/blaming-the-victim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2017 12:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/blaming-the-victim/</guid>
      <description>In the previous 2 blog posts, I discussed some sobering figures on the graduate experience, and how this is probably (partially) related to the lack of advisor evaluation (and training?). And then I read this column from naturejobs.com &amp;ldquo;A growing phobia&amp;rdquo;. The author, with &amp;ldquo;30-plus years as faculty member&amp;rdquo; experience, proposes his (I assume a white man wrote this) solution to a student&amp;rsquo;s fear of interacting with their advisor: &amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The thorny subject of assessing graduate advisors</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-thorny-subject-of-assessing-graduate-advisors/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2017 10:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-thorny-subject-of-assessing-graduate-advisors/</guid>
      <description>One of the most satisfying aspects of graduate school is working together with graduate students to solve fun, important, novel problems. This &amp;ldquo;working together&amp;rdquo; can cover the gradient from supervisor, to advisor, mentor, and collaborator. However, from the perspective of a graduate student, the leadership style implied by these different terms can have important effects on graduate student well-being (last week&amp;rsquo;s news item). In one of the mentioned articles, the authors explicitly quantified three different leadership styles:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graduate student well-being</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/graduate-student-well-being/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2017 08:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/graduate-student-well-being/</guid>
      <description>Graduate student well-being has received a lot of attention lately. As far as I know, it has not reached the level of the urgency as for undergraduate students, but graduate students are exposed to a unique set of challenges too. Two recent studies quantified these challenges: Student Experience Survey 2017: investigating well-being at university and Work organization and mental health problems in PhD students. The second study also argues convincingly that these challenges are unique to the graduate school experience, and are not shared with similar persons in other contexts, such as for instance employees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practical workplace advice by Anne Krook</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/practical-workplace-advice-by-anne-krook/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2017 11:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/practical-workplace-advice-by-anne-krook/</guid>
      <description>Anne Krook has a page full of practical advice on how to get a non-academic employment, which is something that I have been looking for for a long time. So here is the link, and all beginning grad students should consult this page in the first semester of their program. She even has a post titled &amp;ldquo;can non-academic careers be Plan A yet?&amp;rdquo;!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How NOT to get a postdoc (or post PhD) position</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/how-not-to-get-a-postdoc-or-post-phd-position/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2017 10:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/how-not-to-get-a-postdoc-or-post-phd-position/</guid>
      <description>Great story,&amp;nbsp;with a clear message that is equally applicable to non-academic jobs after your PhD or MSc degree: you should be thinking about this during your graduate work, and not wait until you are almost done. Below, I have taken the her final paragraph, and I have made it a little bit more general (the bold sections are my changes):&amp;ldquo;In general, I’ve seen that the people who get ahead in [academic ecology]&amp;nbsp;the job market&amp;nbsp;are those who have a clear vision of what [research]&amp;nbsp;job&amp;nbsp;they want to pursue and why it matters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graduate click-bait: 4 Reasons Graduate Students Shouldn’t Have to Work Weekends</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/graduate-click-bait-4-reasons-graduate-students-shouldnt-have-to-work-weekends/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 10:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/graduate-click-bait-4-reasons-graduate-students-shouldnt-have-to-work-weekends/</guid>
      <description>Despite the click-bait nature of the blog,this blog post has some perspectives that a lot of graduate students in our department will probably be able to relate to. Now I just wonder how many faculty members have a different perspective.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is doing a PhD a waste of time?</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/is-doing-a-phd-a-waste-of-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 16:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/is-doing-a-phd-a-waste-of-time/</guid>
      <description>Some people definitely think so. These types of articles crop up regularly. Here is a recent version of this type of analysis that re-appeared in Medium, but is originally from 2010. These are like the villain in a horror movie, every time you think he is finally dead, ominous music fills the theatre. The linked-to article has some aspects that set it apart, though. It provides a voice of faculty members, in addition to some short-writing gems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying for non-faculty jobs - advice?</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/applying-for-non-faculty-jobs-advice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 14:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/applying-for-non-faculty-jobs-advice/</guid>
      <description>Every field is guilty of some form of navel gazing. Hence the abundance on how to apply for faculty jobs. Margaret Kosmala wrote a&amp;nbsp;recentish blog post on this, with some advice I agree with, but also some I do not agree with. For instance, often departments fight over every single word in a job ad, so showing that you understand the needs that will be filled by the position (i.e., your contributions to the department and university) are important.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life after (or instead of) academia</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/life-after-or-instead-of-academia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2016 13:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/life-after-or-instead-of-academia/</guid>
      <description>Nature&amp;nbsp;summarized a recent report&amp;nbsp;that followed-up researchers after they left university. The tone of the article reflects a bit of the surprise that &amp;ldquo;Guess what: And they are happy!&amp;ldquo;. Our department recently identified what jobs our MSc and PhD students have 5-10 years post graduation, and 42% end up in a research scientist position outside of academia, compared to only 13% in a faculty position, and 16% pursuing an academic training position (PhD or postdoc).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The most important piece of advice?</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-most-important-piece-of-advice/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 12:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-most-important-piece-of-advice/</guid>
      <description>Here is a great post, over on ProfHacker, about advice to new grad students: An open letter to new graduate students, by Brian Croxall.&amp;nbsp;While I agree with most of these topics with varying degrees, they did not include the most important piece of advise, probably because it is so obvious: ask questions. Our role as advisors is to advise, but we can only do this if we get questions. Come in my office, send me an email, skype, whatever.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>