<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ingrid Ng on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/ingrid-ng/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ingrid Ng on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 16:16:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/ingrid-ng/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Talking to...</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/talking-to.../</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 16:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/talking-to.../</guid>
      <description>As you probably noticed, we do lots of interdisciplinary research in this lab. A group of undergraduate students approached this question for a 4th year class, and made a website that approaches interdisciplinary research from, you guessed it, several different perspectives. One of the activities they did was interviewing a wide range of people with this question in mind. Two of those persons where Ingrid and myself. And I will leave it up to you to find those,&amp;nbsp;embarrassing ?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discussing place-based education ...</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/discussing-place-based-education-.../</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2012 16:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/discussing-place-based-education-.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; outside in the Arboretum, with our First Year Seminar class. The (only?) advantage of an early spring this year.

Although Ingrid would probably point out that our discussions, even in the Arboretum,
&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip; had been sitting on the land, instead of having roots within&amp;nbsp;it.&amp;rdquo; (Laura Piersol, Canadian Journal of Environmental Education, 2010, 15:198-209)But how to design a university course to have its roots within the land? It is easier to do this in the context of a field course, but with a Monday-Wednesday 8:30-10 am lecture slot?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tangled bank</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/tangled-bank/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2012 08:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/tangled-bank/</guid>
      <description>What do these four, apparently very unconnected items, have in common?
&amp;nbsp;http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2012/02/lake-vostok-drilled/
http://www.thecleanestline.com/2012/02/cerro-torre-deviations-from-reason.htmlStar wars: the clone wars
http://www.vpacademic.uoguelph.ca/fys/seminars/My life used to be easy.
I was a scientist,&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;climber (a long time ago),&amp;nbsp;father, and a&amp;nbsp;teacher. And now suddenly these separate aspects of &amp;nbsp;my life got sucked into a vortex, all thanks to reading some passages of Aldo Leopold&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Land Ethic&amp;rdquo; for the First Year Seminar course Ingrid and I have designed.&amp;nbsp;These items literally came across my desk (RSS reader, watching TV with the kids, teaching a course) in a 2 day period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making the story whole again</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/making-the-story-whole-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 11:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/making-the-story-whole-again/</guid>
      <description>Ingrid is featured in theAt Guelph! &amp;nbsp;I repeat, Ingrid is featured in the At Guelph! It is not her whole story, of course, but it does provide key aspects of her story.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying to read an article...</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/trying-to-read-an-article.../</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2011 16:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/trying-to-read-an-article.../</guid>
      <description>Karl recently cited this PNAS article in his blog post about the link between environment and society. I started reading it but could not get past the third sentence in the abstract; just those three sentences gave me plenty to think about.

Sentence 1: &amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;the human condition is tightly linked to environmental condition.&amp;rdquo;
I absolutely agree! E.g. The Forsaken Garden by Nancy Ryley - I just started reading this book, about a CBC documentary filmmaker who got struck with &amp;ldquo;environmental illness&amp;rdquo; in the 70&amp;rsquo;s at the height of her career.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three words, a world of difference</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/three-words-a-world-of-difference/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2011 11:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/three-words-a-world-of-difference/</guid>
      <description>I am teaching a field course in Algonquin this summer, and I &amp;ldquo;stress&amp;rdquo;, i.e. grade, two components of field work during this course: a group science project, and an individual natural history project. So the distinction (and similarities) between qualitative and quantitative are on the forefront of mind. This if, of course, compounded by Ingrid who will bring the qualitative approach into the hypothetico-deductive, quantitative, bastion that Integrative Biology is, after years of being exposed to Tom Nudds&amp;rsquo;s beating the bush ;-)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2011 11:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/presentation/</guid>
      <description>Since I started reading a lot of long-form articles on the internet, I have been exposed to a lot of great ideas, and great writing. The latest is an article by Steven Shapin in the London Review of Books, The Darwin Show. He synthesized 14 (fourteen!) books that appeared around the celebration of his 200th birthday in 2009. In it, he explores a lot of interesting themes, and one of the main ones revolves around why this is such a big deal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative vs. qualitative?</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/quantitative-vs.-qualitative/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2011 11:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/quantitative-vs.-qualitative/</guid>
      <description>Ingrid and I had a discussion the other day about whether quantitative or qualitative data make a more lasting impression. As you might have guessed, I am more on the quantitative side, and Ingrid more on the qualitative side ;-) And me being me, I created a visual scenario about a result from Ingrid&amp;rsquo;s thesis (the importance of deep community in successful conservation) that was applied in 100 new conservation efforts (or replicate experiments, without controls, though).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the L word</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-l-word/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2010 09:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-l-word/</guid>
      <description>If I could meet any person, dead or alive, real or fiction, I think one of my top choices would be Steve Irwin. I&amp;rsquo;d want to meet him out in the bush, maybe in Australia, maybe help him re-locate a croc. Afterwards, we might talk about conservation and peace and wilderness. Or, more accurately, he&amp;rsquo;d talk, and I&amp;rsquo;d just nod vigorously in agreement while reveling in his radiance.
Steve Irwin is famously known for his larger-than-life television series Crocodile Hunter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Empty Cups</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/empty-cups/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2010 14:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/empty-cups/</guid>
      <description>Very occasionally, I will brave North American culture and go see a movie on a ridiculously big screen with a ridiculously big bag of popcorn. Last December, a friend convinced me to not only go see Avatar on the big screen, but to watch it in 3-D with her. I was blown away. Though I find the current 3-D craze to be, well, crazy, I have to admit that it brought a certain enchantment to the fantasy planet Pandora.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecofeminism: not just tree-hugging and hairy legs</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/ecofeminism-not-just-tree-hugging-and-hairy-legs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2010 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/ecofeminism-not-just-tree-hugging-and-hairy-legs/</guid>
      <description>In March 2009, the Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies undergraduate program (among others) was cut at Guelph. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t involved in the issue myself, but knew a few people who rallied against this decision. They cited it as ironic evidence that feminism is far from being a finished movement. At the time, I only saw a superficial link between the Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies program cut and feminism; I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what feminism really was.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How much for that polar bear?</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/how-much-for-that-polar-bear/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2010 22:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/how-much-for-that-polar-bear/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;The federal government wants to put a price tag on polar bears,&amp;rdquo; begins this recent Globe and Mail article. It goes on to explain that Environment Canada wants to determine the socio-economic value of the iconic arctic species. This includes things like the bear&amp;rsquo;s consumptive value, cultural value, scientific value, educational value, aesthetic value, existence value, and so on. How much does each &amp;ldquo;additional unit of polar bear&amp;rdquo; or each &amp;ldquo;additional hectare of habitat&amp;rdquo; bring to the nation?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bike Lessons</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/bike-lessons/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 19:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/bike-lessons/</guid>
      <description>I am Ingrid, a returning member of the Cottenie lab. This is my first post, and it comes at one of those in-between times in my life. I am in between finishing a two-month bike tour and starting a three- (or four, or more&amp;hellip;?) year PhD. It&amp;rsquo;s been an interesting process, returning from the tour and re-integrating back into society.
First, a little about the tour. It was one of the best and most challenging things I have ever done.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are you? Zooplankton? Hahahahahahahaha.</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/what-are-you-zooplankton-hahahahahahahaha./</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2010 17:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/what-are-you-zooplankton-hahahahahahahaha./</guid>
      <description>After a whole month of preparations, it finally happened: the procession of species. It started a little bit late for us, since I had a race in the morning. But thanks to cell phones, we could join the parade half way through. Kobe was really excited and waiting for the first sign of the parade and the rest of the lab.
Here are some random pictures of the different species and musicians bringing life music.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The latest Birdfish</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-latest-birdfish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2010 18:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-latest-birdfish/</guid>
      <description>The Churchill Northern Studies Centre has hosted researchers from the Cottenie lab for the past couple years. This year we were invited to contribute a short write-up on our summer 2009 field season. You can read the article here:
http://www.churchillscience.ca/documents/Newsletter_Winter_2010.pdf
Also, be sure to check out the CNSC&amp;rsquo;s website for a preview of their new facility! The staff and volunteers at the CNSC are very supportive and a terrific resource for anyone doing science in the north.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More costumes</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/more-costumes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2010 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/more-costumes/</guid>
      <description>How many do you need to make a costume? Apparently more than 5. However, based on this last evening, we now have a full design, including the know-how on how to make it. So the next time we meet, we should have 6 full Daphnia costumes for the parade.&amp;nbsp;4 degrees to work with papier mache, your quality education at work
To illustrate that this is part of the rostrum, all you dirty minds&amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let the costumes begin!</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/let-the-costumes-begin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Mar 2010 10:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/let-the-costumes-begin/</guid>
      <description>Well, as Karl has mentioned our lab will be participating as a horde of zooplankton in the KW Procession of Species Parade. The parade is as much about encouragaing local expressions of art as it is about showcasing biodiversity. With that in mind we set out yesterday to stretch our creativity and construct a prototype of our first costume. We decided that Daphnia would be our main inspiration and started on a carapace and post abdomen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Awards galore</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/awards-galore/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2010 11:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/awards-galore/</guid>
      <description>Amanda and Ingrid both received an NSERC award: Amanda to finish her MSc, and Ingrid to start her PhD. Now she will have to make a decision ;-) Running a lab with such talented people is easy, I hardly have to do anything myself.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>