<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>statistics on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/statistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in statistics on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 13:51:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://karl-cottenie.github.io/tags/statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Significance versus explanation</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/significance-versus-explanation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 13:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/significance-versus-explanation/</guid>
      <description>Next time I have to teach the difference between explanation and significance, this will be my go-to example: &amp;ldquo;Scientific aptitude better explains poor responses to teaching of evolution than psychological conflicts&amp;rdquo; by Mead et al. in Nature Ecology &amp;amp; Evolution.
The article has several figures that look like this:
The P-value looks amazing (9 x 10^-15), but the spread is equally large. I would not even want to guess what the R-square of that relationship is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Problem in R: how to create a .Rprofile that does not hide important information ...</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/problem-in-r-how-to-create-a-.rprofile-that-does-not-hide-important-information-.../</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2017 15:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/problem-in-r-how-to-create-a-.rprofile-that-does-not-hide-important-information-.../</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; but still is specific to each R script file. For instance, a lot of R users in our group load their packages at the top of their R scripts. Often, these packages are the same, but sometimes they add a different one for a specific type of analysis. I use the tidyverse all the time, and in some analyses vegan. A school of thought would be to automatically add these package to the start up using a .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Students learn the most from each other</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/students-learn-the-most-from-each-other/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2017 09:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/students-learn-the-most-from-each-other/</guid>
      <description>This is something we have known for the last 10 years (or 20) through for instance the research done by Eric Mazur and collaborators.They showed that using peer instruction improved student learning of physics concepts by 20% in a real-world, class setting, compared to a &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; lecture-based approach with the sage on the stage imparting their wisdom to the young susceptible minds!
That is a fine example of a very deliberate teaching practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Best thank you ever</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/best-thank-you-ever/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 10:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/best-thank-you-ever/</guid>
      <description>And this is another (random) example of why R is so awesome:
http://www.masalmon.eu/2017/04/08/spocc/</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standing on the shoulders of giants</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/standing-on-the-shoulders-of-giants/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 14:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/standing-on-the-shoulders-of-giants/</guid>
      <description>I am currently teaching a graduate &amp;ldquo;Stats&amp;rdquo; course, which is more a historical exploration of statistical issues in ecology, led by grad students. As part of the course, we are also exploring best practices in R and ecological data management. So naturally we covered Brian McGill&amp;rsquo;s 10 commandments for good data management, and his follow-up post with an example application of these recommendations with a toy data set.
I decided afterwards to do the challenge, and with our weekly University of Guelph R Users group (UGRU) we walked through the code line by line, and discussed why certain lines were included, alternative ways to code them, advantages and disadvantages of these alternative approaches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Only a hammer in your toolbox</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/only-a-hammer-in-your-toolbox/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Dec 2012 08:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/only-a-hammer-in-your-toolbox/</guid>
      <description>Talk about climate change, and be sure that your analyses are rock solid, because you will get some serious backlash. What interests me most is the danger of &amp;ldquo;if the only tool in your toolbox is a hammer, everything will look like a nail&amp;rdquo; thinking.
http://www.statisticsblog.com/2012/12/the-surprisingly-weak-case-for-global-warming/&amp;nbsp;is a blog post written by a graduate statistics student, with this summary:
&amp;ldquo;TL;DR (scientific version): Based solely on year-over-year changes in surface temperatures, the net increase since 1881 is fully explainable as a non-independent random walk with no trend.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R-hipster confession</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/r-hipster-confession/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2012 10:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/r-hipster-confession/</guid>
      <description>I sometimes think of myself as a science nerd, but then I read Benjamin Mako Hill&amp;rsquo;s computing set-up, and suddenly it&amp;rsquo;s like reading the uber science nerd manifesto. Amazingly consistent and hard-core, every single step of his work flow. And where our work flows overlap is probably in R:
&amp;nbsp;&amp;ldquo;R is slow and using it with big datasets gives one plenty of time to reflect on this fact. But R is also expressive, elegant, and concise for numerical and statistical work so I happily suffer through it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Context is everything</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/context-is-everything/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 10:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/context-is-everything/</guid>
      <description>An interesting paper in Science by Stumpf and Porter&amp;nbsp;takes a hard look at &amp;ldquo;general&amp;rdquo; power laws in science:
&amp;ldquo;A striking feature that has attracted considerable attention is the apparent ubiquity of power-law relationships in empirical data. However, although power laws have been reported in areas ranging from finance and molecular biology to geophysics and the Internet, the data are typically insufficient and the mechanistic insights are almost always too limited for the identification of power-law behavior to be scientifically useful (see the figure).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Musical stats</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/musical-stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2011 10:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/musical-stats/</guid>
      <description>Who thought stats would enter into every aspect of life? What about a Belgian dj duo called Mumbai Science, with the track &amp;ldquo;Ancova&amp;rdquo;?

And this thanks to 2 Many Dj&amp;rsquo;s and Music for Life 2011.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fun with stats</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/fun-with-stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2011 09:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/fun-with-stats/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes stats are sad funny (see this post), and sometimes both fun funny and timely. Seethe latest from PhD Comics:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to lie with politics (and statistics)</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/how-to-lie-with-politics-and-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2011 10:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/how-to-lie-with-politics-and-statistics/</guid>
      <description>Great analysis about the usage of figures in politics:&amp;nbsp;http://flowingdata.com/2011/12/12/fox-news-still-makes-awesome-charts/
What&amp;rsquo;s wrong with this figure?

See the original post for the answer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abstraction - or making explicit connections</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/abstraction-or-making-explicit-connections/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2011 14:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/abstraction-or-making-explicit-connections/</guid>
      <description>One of the items in the grading rubric Marianne Staempfli and I developed for concept maps is the importance of cross links in the arrangement of the concept map:
&amp;ldquo;Cross links show complex relationships between two or more distinct segments of the concept map&amp;rdquo;It is one of the reasons why I am currently involved in a collaboration (among some others) on genome (or transposon) ecology by co-advising Brent Saylor with Ryan Gregory, and on anthropology in ecology by co-advising Ingrid Ng with Bob Jickling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Datateller</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/datateller/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 10:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/datateller/</guid>
      <description>As I recently noticed, the majority of my posts here are unconsciously driven by the courses that I am preparing. The couple of posts on natural history and science are basically an illustration to my field course that I will be teaching next week (hopefully I will get some time to blog from the field). And in the fall, I will be teaching a grad stats course for the first time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What can science learn from Google?</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/what-can-science-learn-from-google/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2010 14:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/what-can-science-learn-from-google/</guid>
      <description>That is the finishing sentence from&amp;nbsp;this article. The author tries to argue that theory and the scientific method is getting obsolete in this day and age, using Google as a role model:
But faced with massive data, this approach to science — hypothesize, model, test — is becoming obsolete. [&amp;hellip;] There is now a better way. Petabytes allow us to say: &amp;ldquo;Correlation is enough.&amp;rdquo; We can stop looking for models. We can analyze the data without hypotheses about what it might show.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eelgrass communities - An update</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/eelgrass-communities-an-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2010 21:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/eelgrass-communities-an-update/</guid>
      <description>I recently gave a brief project update to the gang. Here are the nuts and bolts of my undergrad thesis (I’ll try to stay brief): -Eelgrass meadows are important. They provide habitat for dozens of fish and invertebrate species, stabilize sediment, and cycle carbon and nutrients. Meadows are found in shallow coastal waters on the East and West coasts of North America. Seagrass meadows are globally threatened.
-The community dynamics of eelgrass meadows in temperate zones are largely not understood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The power of graphics</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-power-of-graphics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2010 16:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/the-power-of-graphics/</guid>
      <description>Intelligent persons have written wonderful books about creating good graphs. Today, I received two graphs in my Google Reader, and they make such powerful/funny statements that I had to show them, especially since they are visually so comparable.
In the funny category:

In the powerful category (click here for the original article with more powerful visuals):

It&amp;rsquo;s very unlikely that anything in my research career will produce anything that funny, or could influence the voting behaviour of a whole nation, but we can only try.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypotheses or data first? Update 2</title>
      <link>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/hypotheses-or-data-first-update-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 15:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karl-cottenie.github.io/post/hypotheses-or-data-first-update-2/</guid>
      <description>Since we seem to be on a roll on the what should come first in science, this Nature article actually presents a much better written and argued case in favour of combining the strengths of both approaches (maybe scientists should do what they are good at, science, and leave the writing to, journalists with a PhD?). Some of the costs for doing these genome studies: US$1 billion. How does that stack up to other funding, I have no idea, but this is a big number.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>