<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>metacommunity on Cottenie Lab</title>
    <link>/tags/metacommunity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in metacommunity on Cottenie Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/metacommunity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Distinctive macroinvertebrate communities in a subtropical river network</title>
      <link>/publication/zawalski-2019-jfe/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/zawalski-2019-jfe/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Synchrony in metacommunities</title>
      <link>/post/synchrony-in-metacommunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2013 06:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/synchrony-in-metacommunities/</guid>
      <description>A new year, a new publication, this time with Shubha and Jurek: &amp;ldquo;Population synchrony decreases with richness and increases with environmental ﬂuctuations in an experimental metacommunity&amp;rdquo; in Oecologia. We continued our work with specialization in metacommunities, but this time looked at the implications on population synchrony.
Key figure:
We found, as predicted, that:
the synchrony between populations of a specialist species&amp;nbsp;within a metacommunity is more influenced by environmental fluctuations compared to a generalist speciesthat increasing species richness decreased individual population synchronyWhile these results make perfect sense from an ecological point of view, getting this paper published was not so straightforward because of the unbalanced experimental design we had to use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variation decomposition is a zombie idea?</title>
      <link>/post/variation-decomposition-is-a-zombie-idea/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2013 09:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/variation-decomposition-is-a-zombie-idea/</guid>
      <description>Another post as a response to something written by Jeremy Fox! I think it becomes time that I meet him in person so that I can address him by “Jeremy” instead of “Dr. Fox”, “Fox”, or “the author”. I tried to remove all the salesmanship from my response, though, because I wanted to make sure that 1) I summarized his blog post correctly, and 2) expressed my thoughts as clearly as possible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distribution of unionid freshwater mussels depends on the distribution of host fishes on a regional scale</title>
      <link>/publication/schwalb-2013-dd/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/schwalb-2013-dd/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why consistent terminology is important</title>
      <link>/post/why-consistent-terminology-is-important/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2012 05:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/why-consistent-terminology-is-important/</guid>
      <description>Some time ago, I received this email from a grad student:&amp;ldquo;Do you know the blog zombies ideas in ecology?? I think this is the kind of ideas that could interest you. After reading all these chase papers I just find myself completely lost in the meaning and use of words such as stochastic, random and neutral….&amp;nbsp;This text kind of help me (it’s a critic of the use of these terms in community ecology) http://oikosjournal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colonization rates and species richness</title>
      <link>/post/colonization-rates-and-species-richness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2012 06:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/colonization-rates-and-species-richness/</guid>
      <description>Our first publication from the amazing spanish pond system set-up by Andy Green and his group, but especially with the hard work of Dagmar Frisch, who has the patience of a saint to keep collaborating with me: &amp;ldquo;Strong Spatial Influence on Colonization Rates in a Pioneer Zooplankton Metacommunity&amp;rdquo; in Plos One.
Each published article is unique in its calvary to publication. Most often, this is not visible to the reader, although sometimes you can tell that certain parts in the manuscript are clearly added on to satisfy a reviewer&amp;rsquo;s pet peeve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metacommunity terminology</title>
      <link>/post/metacommunity-terminology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Apr 2012 09:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/metacommunity-terminology/</guid>
      <description>The title of my &amp;ldquo;Teaching Philosophy&amp;rdquo; statement (that I completely rewrite every year), is &amp;ldquo;Research-Teaching-Learning Link&amp;rdquo;. In it, I try to point out the obvious and maybe not so obvious connections between these different aspects of my professional life. One of the items that is hardest to prove, though, is how teaching can inform my day-to-day research focus.
And now I can finally provide evidence for this: our comment in Trends in Ecology and Evolution &amp;ldquo;The terminology of metacommunity ecology&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common versus rare species in a metacommunity context</title>
      <link>/post/common-versus-rare-species-in-a-metacommunity-context/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2011 11:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/common-versus-rare-species-in-a-metacommunity-context/</guid>
      <description>It is finally online, the first publication from the Brazilian side of the lab ;-). In this article, we made competing predictions about how common and rare species should behave in a metacommunity context. The, very surprising, result was that both common and rare species reacted very similarly to environmental gradients, which was very counterintuitive from both a metacommunity and macro-ecology point of view.

Another side effect of this study was our new definition for rareness, based on a slightly subjective but less arbitrary definition compared to other studies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy day - sad day, part 1</title>
      <link>/post/happy-day-sad-day-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2011 09:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/happy-day-sad-day-part-1/</guid>
      <description>All good things come to an end. And now it is Amanda&#39;s time to leave. She successfully defended her thesis &#34;Zooplankton metacommunity responses to environmental change in the sub-arctic&#34;. At this point, there are 3 manifestations of her work:Amanda&#39;s electronic thesis link: the UoG library now provides an electronic reference for all theses, which will increase the exposure and accessibility of the research.Her presentation, that is the perfect example of how we should present results to a larger audience</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dispersal limitation of unionid mussels and implications for their conservation</title>
      <link>/publication/schwalb-2011-fb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/schwalb-2011-fb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental and spatial controls of biotic assemblages in a discrete semi-terrestrial habitat: comparison of organisms with different dispersal abilities sampled in the same plots</title>
      <link>/publication/hajek-2011-jb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/hajek-2011-jb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A metacommuntiy or a self-organized system?</title>
      <link>/post/a-metacommuntiy-or-a-self-organized-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2010 10:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/a-metacommuntiy-or-a-self-organized-system/</guid>
      <description>It is always interesting to read how scientists read, understand, and interpret articles in very different way. You can encounter this most often for your own results when you&amp;nbsp;present at a conference or seminar, and you get questions that throw you in a hoop, and&amp;nbsp;track the articles that refer to one of your publications (admit it, you do it too): often the first response is &#34;how could they interpret my text/data/interpretation in that context?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The relative importance of dispersal and local processes in structuring phytoplankton communities in a set of highly interconnected ponds</title>
      <link>/publication/vanormelingen-2008-fb/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/vanormelingen-2008-fb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metacommunity Structure: Synergy of Biotic Interactions as Selective Agents and Dispersal as Fuel</title>
      <link>/publication/cottenie-2004-e/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2004 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/cottenie-2004-e/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connectivity and cladoceran species richness in a metacommunity of shallow lakes</title>
      <link>/publication/cottenie-2003-fb/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2003 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/cottenie-2003-fb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zooplankton Metacommunity Structure: Regional Vs. Local Processes in Highly Interconnected Ponds</title>
      <link>/publication/cottenie-2003-e/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2003 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/cottenie-2003-e/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>